1
00:00:18,080 --> 00:00:20,580
华沙  1939年

2
00:01:55,140 --> 00:01:56,900
-是席皮尔曼先生吗  -你好
- Mr. Szpilman? - Hello.

3
00:01:57,040 --> 00:01:59,670
我是特地来拜访您的  我很喜欢您的演奏
I came specially to meet you.I love your playing.

4
00:01:59,810 --> 00:02:00,500
你是哪位
Who are you?

5
00:02:00,670 --> 00:02:03,870
我叫多萝塔  我是裘瑞克的妹妹
My name's Dorota, I am Jurek's sister.

6
00:02:04,010 --> 00:02:04,910
您流血了
You're bleeding!

7
00:02:05,050 --> 00:02:06,640
没关系
It's nothing.

8
00:02:06,750 --> 00:02:08,040
走吧  多萝塔
Come Dorota

9
00:02:08,180 --> 00:02:10,650
过些时日你大可写爱慕信给他  但现在时机不对
You can write him a fan letter later.This isn't the best time. Come on.

10
00:02:10,750 --> 00:02:13,080
裘瑞克  你过去都把她藏在哪里的
Jurek, where have you been hiding her?

11
00:02:17,560 --> 00:02:19,990
-我不知道要带什么  -你老是带太多东西
- I don't know what to take. - You always take too much.

12
00:02:21,830 --> 00:02:23,060
你要带几只提箱
How many suitcases are you taking?

13
00:02:23,200 --> 00:02:28,400
你觉得呢  我要带上西蒙叔父的肖像画吗
What do you think, should I take uncle Szymon's portrait?

14
00:02:28,540 --> 00:02:31,130
带不带随便你  你自己决定
Take it, don't take it,take what you like.

15
00:02:31,710 --> 00:02:33,260
你不知道我急出病来了吗
Can't you see I'm worried sick?

16
00:02:33,410 --> 00:02:35,970
他就要回家了 他会没事的
He'll come home, he'll be alright.

17
00:02:36,110 --> 00:02:38,270
你有另一只和这个一样的箱子
You should have another case just...

18
00:02:38,410 --> 00:02:40,140
妈妈  瓦列迪克回家了
Mama, Wladek is home!

19
00:02:40,280 --> 00:02:43,250
感谢老天  瓦列迪克
Thank God. Wladek!

20
00:02:43,920 --> 00:02:46,750
-你受伤了吗  -一点小伤  不要紧的
- You're wounded? - No, it was nothing.

21
00:02:46,890 --> 00:02:47,910
我都忧虑成疾了
I've been worried sick.

22
00:02:48,050 --> 00:02:50,520
我告诉过她不用担心  你要随身带着证件
I told her not to worry.You had your papers on you.

23
00:02:50,660 --> 00:02:53,250
如果你被炸到的话  他们就晓得该把你送到那儿去
If you'd been hit by a bomb,they'd know where to take you.

24
00:02:53,390 --> 00:02:58,160
亨瑞  别...别说那种话  愿上帝宽恕你
Henryk, don't say things like that.God forbid. God forbid.

25
00:02:58,300 --> 00:02:59,530
爸爸  瓦列迪克回来了
Papa, Wladek is home.

26
00:02:59,670 --> 00:03:01,000
我怎么跟你说的  你在做什么
What did I tell you? What are you doing?

27
00:03:01,130 --> 00:03:03,530
有谁看见我的宽边帽
Is anybody see my hat with the wide brim?

28
00:03:04,400 --> 00:03:06,340
他们在进行轰炸  广播关闭了
They've bombed us. We're off the air.

29
00:03:06,470 --> 00:03:08,630
华沙不是唯一的广播站
Warsaw is not the only radio station.

30
00:03:09,140 --> 00:03:10,910
收拾行李  亲爱的  把你的东西打包好
Pack, darling.Get your things packed.

31
00:03:11,040 --> 00:03:11,870
我们要到哪里去
Where are we going?

32
00:03:12,010 --> 00:03:14,140
-离开华沙  -离开华沙去哪里
- Out of Warsaw. - Out of Warsaw where?

33
00:03:14,280 --> 00:03:15,870
你没听说吗
You haven't heard?

34
00:03:16,020 --> 00:03:16,640
听说什么
Heard what?

35
00:03:16,720 --> 00:03:17,650
你没看见报纸吗
Haven't you seen the paper?

36
00:03:17,750 --> 00:03:18,740
没有
No

37
00:03:18,890 --> 00:03:19,650
报纸在哪里
Where's the paper?

38
00:03:19,790 --> 00:03:21,410
我拿来包东西了
I used it for packing.

39
00:03:21,560 --> 00:03:24,120
-她把报纸拿来包东西  -政府已经迁到陆柏林了
- She used it for packing. - The government has moved to Lublin.

40
00:03:24,260 --> 00:03:26,120
所以四肢健全的男人都必须离开这座城市
22All able-body men must leave the city, go across the river,

41
00:03:26,260 --> 00:03:28,490
为了建立一道新的防御线
set up a new line of defense.

42
00:03:28,700 --> 00:03:31,430
除了女人  没人还留在这栋房子里
There isn't anybody left to the building, only the women.

43
00:03:31,570 --> 00:03:32,430
男人都已经离开了
The men have gone.

44
00:03:32,570 --> 00:03:35,800
其他人去建立新防御线  你打算做什么
What do you think you'll do while they set up a new line of defense?

45
00:03:35,940 --> 00:03:37,670
拖着你的箱子到处游荡吗
Wonder around with your suitcases?

46
00:03:37,740 --> 00:03:39,230
收拾一下  瓦列  没时间了
Pack, Wladek. There's no time.

47
00:03:39,370 --> 00:03:40,670
我哪儿都不去
I'm not going anywhere.

48
00:03:40,810 --> 00:03:43,400
很好  我也不要离开
Good. I'm not going anywhere either.

49
00:03:43,540 --> 00:03:45,880
不要胡闹了  我们必需在一起
Don't be ridiculous,we've got to keep together.

50
00:03:46,010 --> 00:03:47,670
听着  如果要死的话
Look. If I'm going to die,

51
00:03:47,670 --> 00:03:49,610
我宁愿死在自己家里  我不走
I prefer to die in my own home, staying put.

52
00:03:49,750 --> 00:03:50,510
上帝宽恕你
God forbid.

53
00:03:50,650 --> 00:03:53,020
别吵了  电台有重要消息  听
Shut up, I've got something. Listen.

54
00:03:53,150 --> 00:03:55,620
据BBC报导
...from the BBC in London.

55
00:03:55,720 --> 00:04:01,160
英国政府尚未得到任何...
The British government having received no reply...

56
00:04:01,290 --> 00:04:05,200
对德国政府发出的最后通牒的回复
to the observations presented to the German government...

57
00:04:05,330 --> 00:04:08,820
正式向纳粹德国宣战
has declared war on nazi Germany.

58
00:04:09,740 --> 00:04:13,230
-太棒了 太棒了  -预计...
- That's wonderful! Wonderful! - It is expected that...

59
00:04:18,140 --> 00:04:20,110
...在数小时内
...within the next few hours,

60
00:04:20,250 --> 00:04:23,410
法国将发布同样的声明
France will make a similar declaration.

61
00:04:23,550 --> 00:04:27,010
波兰将不再孤立无援
Poland is no longer alone.

62
00:04:32,430 --> 00:04:34,150
太棒了  太棒了
Wonderful, wonderful!

63
00:04:35,730 --> 00:04:38,930
妈妈  这真是一顿美妙的晚餐
Mama, that was a great dinner.

64
00:04:39,070 --> 00:04:40,000
没错
It certainly was.

65
00:04:40,130 --> 00:04:43,330
每当有值得庆贺的事情  你需在饭菜上花心思
When there's something to celebrate,you've got to make an effort.

66
00:04:43,470 --> 00:04:45,700
为大不列颠和法国举杯
Here's to Great Britain and France!

67
00:04:46,470 --> 00:04:48,170
我就说吧
I told you? Didn't I tell you?

68
00:04:48,310 --> 00:04:51,110
一切都会没事
All will be well.

69
00:05:23,680 --> 00:05:24,840
5,003块
Five thousand and three.

70
00:05:24,980 --> 00:05:27,540
全部就这些吗
Is that all?

71
00:05:27,680 --> 00:05:28,310
没错
Yes.

72
00:05:28,450 --> 00:05:31,020
5,003波币 我们就剩下这些了

73
00:05:31,020 --> 00:05:32,890
我们还超出3,003元

74
00:05:33,020 --> 00:05:37,420
你看  最新流动资产限额条例
Look."Further restrictions regarding liquid assets.

75
00:05:37,560 --> 00:05:41,430
犹太人在家中放置现金上限为2,000波币
Jews will be allowed to keep a maximum of 2,000 zlotys at home. "

76
00:05:41,630 --> 00:05:43,150
其余的钱该怎么处理呢
What do we do with the rest?

77
00:05:43,300 --> 00:05:45,590
把它存进银行里  帐户会被冻结
Deposit it in a bank. a blocked account.

78
00:05:45,730 --> 00:05:49,630
银行  谁会笨到把钱存进德国人的银行里
Banks! Who'd be stupid enough to deposit money in a German bank?

79
00:05:49,770 --> 00:05:51,460
我们可以把钱藏起来
We could hide the money.

80
00:05:51,640 --> 00:05:54,700
看这里  我们可以把钱藏在花盆下面
Look here.We can hide the money under the flowerpots.

81
00:05:54,840 --> 00:05:57,900
不  我们要采取通过通过实践考验的办法
no no no, I'll tell you what we'll do.We'll use tried and tested methods.

82
00:05:58,040 --> 00:06:00,670
知道我们上一次是怎么做的吗
You know what we did in the last war?

83
00:06:00,810 --> 00:06:04,440
我们在桌脚凿了个洞  把钱藏进去
We made a hole in the table leg,and hid the money in there.

84
00:06:04,650 --> 00:06:05,810
但如果他们把桌子扛走呢
and suppose they take the table away?

85
00:06:05,950 --> 00:06:07,210
把桌子扛走是什么意思
What do you mean take the table away?

86
00:06:07,350 --> 00:06:09,850
德国人会闯进犹太人家里夺取任何他们想要的东西
the Germans go into Jewish homes and they just take anything they want

87
00:06:09,990 --> 00:06:12,050
家俱  值钱的物品  任何东西
furniture, valuables, anything.

88
00:06:12,190 --> 00:06:12,620
会吗
Do they?

89
00:06:12,690 --> 00:06:15,630
笨蛋  他们怎可能会要这样一张桌子
idiot, Why'd they want to take a table like this?

90
00:06:16,560 --> 00:06:17,530
你到底在干什么
What on earth are you doing?

91
00:06:17,660 --> 00:06:19,430
听着
Listen. Look.

92
00:06:19,570 --> 00:06:21,210
这是最理想的地方
This is the best place for it.

93
00:06:21,210 --> 00:06:23,400
没有人会想到要搜查花盆
No-one would think of looking under the flowerpot.

94
00:06:23,540 --> 00:06:25,770
不  不  听我说  我已经想过了
No, listen. I've been thinking...

95
00:06:25,910 --> 00:06:27,960
-是吗  这想法倒与众不同  -我们该怎么做
- Really? That's a change. - You know what we do?

96
00:06:28,110 --> 00:06:28,940
我们要运用心理学
We use psychology.

97
00:06:29,080 --> 00:06:30,410
运用什么
We use what?

98
00:06:30,540 --> 00:06:33,070
我们把钱和表放在桌上
We leave the money and the watch on the table,

99
00:06:33,210 --> 00:06:36,410
然后像这样把它们遮住
and we cover them like this. In full view.

100
00:06:38,450 --> 00:06:38,970
你是傻瓜吗
Are you stupid?

101
00:06:39,120 --> 00:06:40,220
德国人会到处搜索别的地方
The Germans will search high and low and

102
00:06:40,220 --> 00:06:41,250
我保证他们不会发现这个
 I promised that they never notice it.

103
00:06:41,390 --> 00:06:43,190
这是我见过最愚蠢的事情
That's the stupidest thing I've ever seen.

104
00:06:43,320 --> 00:06:46,850
他们当然会发现  瞧着
Of course they'll notice. Look.Look here.

105
00:06:48,630 --> 00:06:49,250
傻瓜
Idiot.

106
00:06:50,460 --> 00:06:51,590
你说我是傻瓜
And you call me stupid.

107
00:06:51,660 --> 00:06:53,030
那方法很好  那是最不容易被...
that's very good. because that's the last place...

108
00:06:53,170 --> 00:06:54,330
这得花多长时间把钱塞进去啊
This would take hours.

109
00:06:54,470 --> 00:06:56,400
-我们又不赶时间  -那用不了多久
- We're not in a hurry. - It won't take hours.

110
00:06:56,540 --> 00:07:00,700
告诉我  那你要怎么把钱拿出来
How will you get them out? Tell me that

111
00:07:00,840 --> 00:07:04,640
-一张张扯出来吗  -听我说
- You reach them out individually. - No-one listens to me!

112
00:07:04,780 --> 00:07:08,410
安静  拜托有点秩序
Quiet, order, order, please

113
00:07:08,550 --> 00:07:10,240
她是律师 她喜欢秩序
The lawyer, she likes order.

114
00:07:10,380 --> 00:07:11,610
听我说
Listen, just listen.

115
00:07:11,720 --> 00:07:16,680
我们把表放在花盆下  然后把钱塞进小提琴里
Look.The watch we put under the flowerpot and the money we stuff in the violin.

116
00:07:18,390 --> 00:07:20,290
这样我还能弹奏吗
But I'll still be able to play?

117
00:07:20,430 --> 00:07:22,420
放心  会有办法的
You'll find out.

118
00:07:23,160 --> 00:07:25,830
裘瑞克  我是瓦列·席皮尔曼
Jurek? It's Wladek Szpilman.

119
00:07:25,970 --> 00:07:27,490
你好吗
Wladek, how are you?

120
00:07:27,670 --> 00:07:30,260
我们很好  谢谢  你呢
fine, We're fine, thank you.And you?

121
00:07:30,400 --> 00:07:33,030
在这种局势下还算不错
Fine, under the circumstances.

122
00:07:33,170 --> 00:07:37,300
我知道你为什么打电话  我们实在无能为力
I guess I know why you're calling. There's nothing we can do...

123
00:07:37,440 --> 00:07:38,930
电台不会恢复
They won't reopen the station.

124
00:07:39,080 --> 00:07:40,740
是的 我知道 但是裘瑞克...
Yes, I know, but I...

125
00:07:40,880 --> 00:07:43,580
没有音乐  没有波兰人听的广播  什么都没有
No music, nothing,no radios for the Polish.

126
00:07:43,720 --> 00:07:46,310
但我确信像你这样的钢琴家
But sure you'll find work.

127
00:07:46,450 --> 00:07:47,580
会找到工作的
A pianist like you.

128
00:07:47,690 --> 00:07:49,620
或许吧  但是...
Maybe, maybe not, but...

129
00:07:50,660 --> 00:07:52,590
听着  我无意冒犯
listen,don't be offended,but I...

130
00:07:52,660 --> 00:07:55,220
但我打电话来不是为了讨论我以后的工作
didn't call to discuss my future carrier.

131
00:07:55,630 --> 00:07:57,720
我对裘瑞克唠叨了好几个礼拜
I nagged Jurek for weeks and weeks,

132
00:07:57,860 --> 00:07:59,190
最后他投降了  说
and at last he gave in and said...

133
00:07:59,190 --> 00:08:00,890
"好吧 明天和我一起去电台"
"All right, come with me tomorrow",

134
00:08:01,030 --> 00:08:05,130
于是我来了  但他们把电台炸毁了
so I came and...they bombed the station.

135
00:08:05,270 --> 00:08:08,040
能与你那样认识很不错
Meeting you like that was wonderful.

136
00:08:08,170 --> 00:08:12,870
-真的吗  -是的  这...让人记忆深刻
- Really? - Yes, it was unforgettable.

137
00:08:13,010 --> 00:08:14,880
我一直很喜欢您的演奏  席皮尔曼先生
I alwys love your playing, Mr. Szpilman.

138
00:08:15,010 --> 00:08:16,000
请叫我瓦列
Call me Wladek, please.

139
00:08:16,150 --> 00:08:17,910
没有人能像你这样演奏萧邦的曲目
No-one plays Chopin like you.

140
00:08:18,050 --> 00:08:19,610
我希望那是个赞美
I hope it's a compliment.

141
00:08:19,690 --> 00:08:20,910
我当然是这个意思
Of course, I mean it.

142
00:08:21,050 --> 00:08:23,960
我只是...开个玩笑
I was... trying to be funny.

143
00:08:24,090 --> 00:08:26,220
愿意跟我去帕拉迪索喝杯咖啡吗
Should we go Pradiso and have a coffee?

144
00:08:26,360 --> 00:08:27,520
乐意之至
I'd like that.

145
00:08:29,330 --> 00:08:31,230
你呢  你是做什么的
And you, what do you do?

146
00:08:31,360 --> 00:08:33,260
我刚从音乐学校毕业
I finished with the conservatoire.

147
00:08:33,400 --> 00:08:34,090
你是乐师
You're a musician?

148
00:08:34,230 --> 00:08:34,860
是的  只是...
Yes. But only just...

149
00:08:35,000 --> 00:08:37,230
哪样乐器...抱歉 哪样乐器
What instrument? I'am sorry,What instrument?

150
00:08:37,370 --> 00:08:38,630
大提琴
The cello.

151
00:08:38,710 --> 00:08:41,200
我喜欢看女士演奏大提琴
I love to see women playing the cello.

152
00:08:44,940 --> 00:08:46,430
禁止犹太人进入
JEWS FORBIDDEN

153
00:08:46,610 --> 00:08:49,670
真是无礼  他们怎能这样
This is disgraceful.How dare they?

154
00:08:49,820 --> 00:08:52,580
人就是这样  他们比希特勒还希特勒
You know what people are like, they want to be better nazis than Hitler.

155
00:08:52,720 --> 00:08:54,980
-我要去抗议  -算了
- I'm going in there to complain. - No

156
00:08:55,120 --> 00:08:56,880
最好不要  相信我
It's better not, believe me.

157
00:08:57,020 --> 00:08:59,580
这对你来说太屈辱了
It's so humiliating. Someone like you!

158
00:09:04,900 --> 00:09:07,300
我们去别处吧
find somewhere else.

159
00:09:07,430 --> 00:09:08,870
我们可以到公园散步
We can walk in the park.

160
00:09:09,000 --> 00:09:14,840
不  不行  官方有令  犹太人禁止进入公园
No, we can't.Official decree.No Jews allowed in the park.

161
00:09:14,970 --> 00:09:16,410
天啊  你是开玩笑吗
My God. Are you joking?

162
00:09:16,540 --> 00:09:17,740
我没有开玩笑  是真的
I'm not joking, it's true.

163
00:09:17,880 --> 00:09:19,780
我想我们可以坐在长椅上
I suggest we could sit in a bench,

164
00:09:19,910 --> 00:09:21,310
但官方另有禁令 "犹太人禁止坐在公共长椅上"
but another official decree "no Jews allowed on public benches".

165
00:09:22,920 --> 00:09:24,750
这真是荒谬
This is absurd.

166
00:09:24,880 --> 00:09:28,340
我告诉你我们可以做什么吧  我们只能站在这里交谈
I tell what we can do,We can just stand here and talk.

167
00:09:28,490 --> 00:09:31,320
我想这是被允许的  不是吗
and I think we're allowed to do that, don't you?

168
00:09:31,460 --> 00:09:34,980
那么你拉大提琴的  多萝塔  好极了
So, you play the cello. Dorota, That's nice.

169
00:09:35,130 --> 00:09:36,530
你最欣赏的作曲家是谁
And who's your favorite composer?

170
00:09:36,660 --> 00:09:37,650
萧邦  是吗
Chopin? Really? Well...

171
00:09:39,030 --> 00:09:41,930
你得学他的大提琴奏鸣曲  不是吗
you'll have to learn to play his cello sonata, won't you?

172
00:09:42,070 --> 00:09:44,060
那么你呢  瓦列
What about you, Wladek?

173
00:09:45,000 --> 00:09:47,870
也许我可以为你伴奏  我弹钢琴  你拉大提琴
Perhaps I could accompany.Me on the piano, you on the cello.

174
00:09:48,010 --> 00:09:52,240
席皮尔曼先生  你真是太棒太棒了
Mr. Szpilman, you're quite,quite wonderful.

175
00:09:53,910 --> 00:09:55,880
请叫我瓦列
Call me Wladek, please.

176
00:09:56,680 --> 00:10:00,240
华沙特区的犹太人  需配带标志
"Free emblems for Jews in the Warsaw district.

177
00:10:00,390 --> 00:10:03,690
我在此下令  华沙特区所有的犹太人...
I hereby order that all Jews in the Warsaw district...

178
00:10:03,820 --> 00:10:07,050
出门需配带醒目的标志
will wear visible emblems when out of doors.

179
00:10:07,190 --> 00:10:11,930
此令自1939年12月1日起强制执行
This decree will come into force on the first of December, 1939...

180
00:10:12,070 --> 00:10:15,800
适用于12岁以上的犹太人
and applies to all Jews over 12 years of age.

181
00:10:15,940 --> 00:10:19,230
标志需配带于右臂
The emblem will be worn on the right sleeve...

182
00:10:19,370 --> 00:10:23,740
在白底绣上一颗蓝色的大卫王之星
and will represent the blue star of David on a white background.

183
00:10:23,880 --> 00:10:26,850
底布必需要够大
The background must be sufficiently large...

184
00:10:26,980 --> 00:10:31,310
因为星星的顶点间距离要8厘米
for the star to measure eight centimeters from point to point.

185
00:10:31,450 --> 00:10:35,650
线条的宽度必需为1厘米
The width of the arms of the star must be one centimeter.

186
00:10:35,790 --> 00:10:40,660
未遵从此令的犹太人将受严厉惩罚
The Jews that do not respect this decree will be severely punished.

187
00:10:41,260 --> 00:10:43,230
华沙特区首长
Governor of the Warsaw district,

188
00:10:44,900 --> 00:10:46,190
费沙博士
Dr. Fischer. "

189
00:10:49,200 --> 00:10:50,130
我不会戴
I won't wear it.

190
00:10:50,270 --> 00:10:53,640
我不会戴  我不要被贴上标签
I won't wear it.I'm not going to be branded.

191
00:10:57,340 --> 00:10:58,500
让我看看
Let me see this.

192
00:11:03,550 --> 00:11:08,180
这是否意味着我们得自行准备这些臂章
Does it say that we have to provid these armbands ourselves?

193
00:11:08,320 --> 00:11:09,480
我们上哪儿去找
Where will we get them?

194
00:11:09,690 --> 00:11:13,020
不用去找  我们不会戴
we won't to get them. We're not going to wear them.

195
00:11:21,790 --> 00:11:23,660
你

196
00:11:24,790 --> 00:11:26,880
过来

197
00:11:33,080 --> 00:11:34,710
你为什么没有鞠躬

198
00:11:36,450 --> 00:11:38,040
请原凉我

199
00:11:48,930 --> 00:11:50,620
你不准走人行道

200
00:11:52,000 --> 00:11:53,660
走水沟

201
00:12:10,450 --> 00:12:11,680
你看这个了吗
Have you seen this?

202
00:12:11,820 --> 00:12:14,290
怎么了  我正在工作  什么事儿
What? What? I'm working. What?

203
00:12:16,020 --> 00:12:16,750
这是什么
What is this?

204
00:12:18,890 --> 00:12:20,650
这是他们将要安置我们的地方
It's where they're going to put us.

205
00:12:20,790 --> 00:12:22,160
你说"安置我们"是什么意思
What do you mean "put us"?

206
00:12:24,860 --> 00:12:28,560
华沙特区首长费沙博士
"By order of the governor of the Warsaw district, Dr. Fischer...

207
00:12:28,700 --> 00:12:32,260
关于在华沙建立犹太人隔离区的命令
concerning the establishment of the Jewish district in Warsaw.

208
00:12:32,410 --> 00:12:35,430
犹太人隔离区即将建成  所有犹太人...
There'll be created a Jewish district in which all Jews

209
00:12:35,580 --> 00:12:39,030
华沙本地人或外地人  都必需进驻
living in Warsaw or moving to Warsa will have to reside. "

210
00:12:39,180 --> 00:12:40,240
看这里
Look here.

211
00:12:40,680 --> 00:12:42,940
居住在指定区之外的犹太人
"Jews living outside of the prescribed area...

212
00:12:43,080 --> 00:12:48,610
必需在1940年10月31日前迁至隔离区
will have to move to the Jewish district by 31 of October, 1940."

213
00:12:49,790 --> 00:12:51,450
那儿不可能把我们全部装下
They won't get all of us.

214
00:12:51,660 --> 00:12:54,150
那里太小了  华沙有40万犹太人
It's too small.There's 400 thousand of us in Warsaw.

215
00:12:54,290 --> 00:12:57,960
不  36万人  这样便有可能
No, 360 thousand.So it will be easy.

216
00:12:58,100 --> 00:13:00,000
我该怎么办
What am I supposed to do?

217
00:13:01,930 --> 00:13:03,930
你告诉我现在该怎么办
You tell me.

218
00:13:05,570 --> 00:13:06,630
妈妈
Mama?

219
00:13:08,310 --> 00:13:11,040
妈妈 这是什么
Mama, what is it?

220
00:13:12,950 --> 00:13:14,850
20波币
20 zlotys!

221
00:13:15,680 --> 00:13:18,380
我们就剩下这些了  20波币
That's all we have left, 20 zlotys.

222
00:13:22,760 --> 00:13:25,020
20波币可以拿来买什么
What can I buy with 20 zlotys?

223
00:13:26,690 --> 00:13:31,030
我受不了一直吃马铃薯  马铃薯  马铃薯
I'm sick of cooking potatoes,potatoes, potatoes.

224
00:13:38,700 --> 00:13:40,930
就这个价格  这是我的出价
That's the price.That's what I'm offering.

225
00:13:41,070 --> 00:13:43,840
我建议你接受  没人会出更高的价
My advice is to accept.You won't get more from anyone else.

226
00:13:43,980 --> 00:13:46,280
李帕先生  但这可是贝西斯坦牌的

227
00:13:46,280 --> 00:13:48,350
2,000元...我建议你收下吧

228
00:13:48,480 --> 00:13:50,750
你饿肚子的时候怎么办  啃钢琴吗
What are you going to do when you're hungry? Eat the piano?

229
00:13:51,880 --> 00:13:54,380
-滚出去  你这龌龊卑鄙的家伙  -你是怎么回事
- Get out! - What's the matter with you?

230
00:13:54,520 --> 00:13:56,140
我们宁愿把它丢掉  滚

231
00:13:56,140 --> 00:13:57,650
你今天还没吃过东西吧

232
00:13:57,790 --> 00:13:59,490
你在挣扎什么
What are you suffering from?

233
00:14:00,530 --> 00:14:01,860
你们真是疯狂
You people are crazy.

234
00:14:03,300 --> 00:14:06,860
我这是在帮你  2,000元  而且运费由我来付
I'm doing you a favor. Two thousand and I'm paying for the removal.

235
00:14:07,000 --> 00:14:09,020
我甚至不算运费
I'm not even charging for the removal!

236
00:14:10,770 --> 00:14:11,860
你今天还没有吃东西
You haven't eaten today.

237
00:14:12,000 --> 00:14:13,270
你疯了
You're crazy.

238
00:14:13,410 --> 00:14:15,030
拿走吧
Take it.

239
00:14:19,010 --> 00:14:21,980
1940年10月31日

240
00:14:49,940 --> 00:14:50,870
多萝塔
Dorota

241
00:14:52,850 --> 00:14:53,610
嗨
Hello. Hi.

242
00:14:57,020 --> 00:14:58,280
我原本没有要来
I didn't want to come.

243
00:14:59,520 --> 00:15:04,050
我不想看见这一幕  但是我...我控制不了自己
I didn't want to see all this, but...I couldn't stop myself.

244
00:15:04,190 --> 00:15:05,750
你近来好吗
How are you doing?

245
00:15:05,890 --> 00:15:06,320
很好
Fine.

246
00:15:06,460 --> 00:15:07,930
好
Good.

247
00:15:08,660 --> 00:15:09,960
不 不尽然
No, not really.

248
00:15:10,100 --> 00:15:12,360
我表哥被逮捕了
They arrested my cousin.

249
00:15:12,500 --> 00:15:14,690
裘瑞克说他们会释放他的
Jurek says they'll let him out.

250
00:15:16,070 --> 00:15:17,500
真是不幸
This is disgraceful.

251
00:15:18,440 --> 00:15:19,930
不会太久的  别担心
It won't last long. Don't worry.

252
00:15:21,010 --> 00:15:22,770
我对自己也是这么说的
That's what I said myself.

253
00:15:24,480 --> 00:15:25,910
太荒谬了
It's too absurd.

254
00:15:31,050 --> 00:15:33,180
我...我该走了
I... I should go.

255
00:15:36,020 --> 00:15:40,460
后会有期...
Well, I'll see you...soon.

256
00:15:45,200 --> 00:15:46,130
再见
Good-bye.

257
00:16:01,810 --> 00:16:05,010
说实话
Well...to tell the truth,

258
00:16:06,220 --> 00:16:07,620
我原以为情况会更糟
I thought it would be worse.

259
00:16:14,330 --> 00:16:15,620
我们要睡在哪里
Where will we sleep?

260
00:16:16,430 --> 00:16:18,690
我和女孩儿们睡厨房
I sleep in the kitchen with the girls.

261
00:16:18,830 --> 00:16:21,200
你和亨瑞还有爸爸睡这里
You, Henryk and papa, in here.

262
00:16:23,670 --> 00:16:24,430
看
Look.

263
00:16:26,770 --> 00:16:27,830
过来看啊
Come and look.

264
00:17:01,330 --> 00:17:03,250
走开
Go away.

265
00:17:03,280 --> 00:17:04,610
走开  走开
Go away! Go away!

266
00:17:06,750 --> 00:17:08,440
爸爸  爸爸
Papa! Papa!

267
00:17:08,980 --> 00:17:09,780
爸爸
Papa!

268
00:17:11,280 --> 00:17:12,150
爸爸
Papa!

269
00:17:25,670 --> 00:17:26,630
卖出什么了吗
Sell anything?

270
00:17:26,770 --> 00:17:29,130
就卖出一本杜思妥也夫斯基的"白痴"
just one,Dostoyevsky's "Idiot"

271
00:17:29,270 --> 00:17:30,670
3元波币
3 zlotys.

272
00:17:30,800 --> 00:17:32,130
不过比昨天好
Better than yesterday.

273
00:17:32,270 --> 00:17:34,330
3枚肮脏的波币
Three lousy zlotys.

274
00:17:34,470 --> 00:17:36,630
但有人却大把大把的赚钞票
And there are people there making millions.

275
00:17:36,740 --> 00:17:37,330
我知道
I know.

276
00:17:37,480 --> 00:17:39,210
你才不知道呢
You don't know, believe me.

277
00:17:39,810 --> 00:17:42,910
他们贿赂警卫  警卫于是睁一只眼闭一只眼
They bribe the guards,the guards turn a blind eye.

278
00:17:43,050 --> 00:17:47,950
他们大量输入食物 烟酒  法国化妆品
They bring cartloads of food,tobacco, liquor, French cosmetics.

279
00:17:48,090 --> 00:17:50,320
穷人在他们周围死去  他们连痰也没啐一口
And the poor are dying all around and they don't give a damn.

280
00:17:50,460 --> 00:17:54,450
不好意思  请问你看见我丈夫伊沙克 沙曼了吗
Excuse me, have you seen my husband, Izaak Szerman?

281
00:17:54,630 --> 00:17:57,620
一个高大英俊的男人  他蓄着灰色的胡子
A tall handsome man,with a little gray beard.

282
00:17:57,760 --> 00:17:59,360
-没有吗  -恐怕没有
- No? - I'm afraid not.

283
00:17:59,500 --> 00:18:01,260
打扰了
Excuse me.

284
00:18:01,630 --> 00:18:04,430
再见  祝好梦
Good-bye.Sleep well.

285
00:18:04,640 --> 00:18:07,940
但如果看见他  请写信给我好吗
But if you see him, write to me, yes?

286
00:18:08,070 --> 00:18:09,670
伊沙克·沙曼
Izaak Szerman.

287
00:18:24,290 --> 00:18:27,920
为什么非得要有一条非犹太人的街道穿过我们的地方
Why do we have to have a gentile street running through our area?

288
00:18:28,060 --> 00:18:29,890
为什么他们不绕过去
Why can't they go around?

289
00:18:30,030 --> 00:18:34,630
别担心  他们就要建一座桥了  你没听说吗
Don't worry about it. They're about to build a bridge. Haven't you heard?

290
00:18:34,770 --> 00:18:37,460
一座桥?  一个笑话
A bridge! A bridge!Those idiots.

291
00:18:38,300 --> 00:18:40,570
德国人声称他们智商高
The Germans claim to be intelligent.

292
00:18:40,640 --> 00:18:44,440
你知道我怎么想吗  他们根本是不折不扣的白痴
But do you know what I think?I think they're totally stupid.

293
00:18:44,610 --> 00:18:46,480
我有家人要养
I have a family to feed.

294
00:18:46,610 --> 00:18:50,670
却得在这里花上半辈子时间等他们放行
I spend half of my time here...waiting for them to let us through.

295
00:18:50,820 --> 00:18:53,940
他们以为我来这里干嘛  来听音乐的吗
Maybe they think I come here to listen to the music?

296
00:18:53,990 --> 00:18:58,870
-说什么呢  你很急?  -你有意见?

297
00:18:59,040 --> 00:19:03,190
-找点乐子  -对  跳舞

298
00:19:03,670 --> 00:19:06,330
跳舞  跳舞

299
00:19:06,430 --> 00:19:08,590
来  来  跳舞

300
00:19:12,720 --> 00:19:14,510
很好

301
00:19:14,720 --> 00:19:16,680
你去跟他一起跳

302
00:19:18,140 --> 00:19:22,430
闪开  空出地方让这些犹太佬跳舞

303
00:19:25,730 --> 00:19:28,020
你  还有你

304
00:19:34,110 --> 00:19:35,820
跳啊

305
00:19:37,370 --> 00:19:38,330
快点

306
00:19:40,040 --> 00:19:42,200
继续

307
00:19:43,910 --> 00:19:44,910
别停

308
00:19:48,750 --> 00:19:50,500
继续

309
00:19:51,380 --> 00:19:54,010
别停

310
00:19:56,260 --> 00:20:00,930
继续跳  跳快点  继续  犹太佬

311
00:20:01,140 --> 00:20:04,140
继续跳  跳啊

312
00:20:23,080 --> 00:20:24,340
他们回来了
Good, they're here.

313
00:20:26,410 --> 00:20:28,350
耶兹札克·海勒正在等你们
Itzak Heller has been waiting for you.

314
00:20:35,620 --> 00:20:37,150
-有什么事吗  -坐下来  请喝茶
- What's this about? - Sit down, have tea.

315
00:20:37,290 --> 00:20:39,350
等姑娘们回来我再开饭
I'll start lunch when the girls get here.

316
00:20:45,700 --> 00:20:47,500
你来这干什么
So, what are you doing here?

317
00:20:47,670 --> 00:20:50,030
他带饼干来
He brought cakes, he is up

318
00:20:50,800 --> 00:20:54,970
他爸爸做珠宝生意回来  他干得不错  是吧
His father is back in the jewellery business,doing well him.eh?

319
00:20:57,740 --> 00:20:59,040
真令人惊奇  珠宝
Amazing, jewellery.

320
00:21:00,410 --> 00:21:01,340
我们在招人
We're recruiting.

321
00:21:01,480 --> 00:21:02,410
谁在招人
Who is recruiting?

322
00:21:02,550 --> 00:21:05,350
别耍小聪明  我是以朋友的身份来这里
Don't be clever with me. I'm coming as a friend.

323
00:21:05,480 --> 00:21:07,450
全国各地的犹太人涌进城市
They're bringing Jews in from all over the country.

324
00:21:07,590 --> 00:21:09,240
很快隔离区会有50万人
Soon there will be half million people in the ghetto.

325
00:21:09,240 --> 00:21:10,780
我们需要更多的犹太人警察
We need more Jewish police.

326
00:21:10,920 --> 00:21:13,890
更多的犹太人警察
More Jewish police!

327
00:21:14,030 --> 00:21:18,120
你是要我用警棍打那些反抗盖世太保的犹太人?
you mean you want me to beat up Jews in my truncheon and catch the Gestapo

328
00:21:18,260 --> 00:21:19,490
一定要有人做这件事  亨瑞
Someone has got to do it.

329
00:21:19,700 --> 00:21:20,430
但为什么是我
But why me?

330
00:21:20,570 --> 00:21:23,030
我以为你只征召富家子弟
I thought you only recruited boys with rich fathers.

331
00:21:23,170 --> 00:21:25,230
看看我父亲 看看我们  我的意思是...
Look at my father, look at us...I mean

332
00:21:25,370 --> 00:21:26,930
是啊 我在看  这就是为什么我在这里
I'm looking at you, that's why I'm here.

333
00:21:27,070 --> 00:21:28,400
你们全家可以过好一点的生活
Your whole family can have a better life.

334
00:21:28,540 --> 00:21:31,440
你要继续靠卖书维持生存  苟延残喘吗
You want to struggling survive for selling the books in the street?

335
00:21:31,580 --> 00:21:33,010
正是如此
Yes, please.

336
00:21:33,150 --> 00:21:36,050
我是在帮你们
I'm doing you people a favor.

337
00:21:36,180 --> 00:21:37,670
那么你呢  瓦列
What about you,Wladek?

338
00:21:37,780 --> 00:21:40,380
你是位了不起的钢琴家  而我们有很棒的警察爵士乐团
You're a great pianist.We've got a police jazz band.

339
00:21:40,520 --> 00:21:42,110
他们会展开双臂欢迎你加入我们  加入我们吧
They'd welcome you with open arms.Join us.

340
00:21:42,250 --> 00:21:43,050
你没有工作
You've got no work.

341
00:21:43,190 --> 00:21:45,380
谢谢  但我有工作
Thank you, I've got work.

342
00:22:30,400 --> 00:22:32,030
是的  当然
right,yes it is

343
00:22:34,040 --> 00:22:36,560
抱歉  瓦列  他要你停止演奏
I'm sorry,Wladek.he wants you to stop.

344
00:22:38,440 --> 00:22:39,930
是谁要我停止
Who wants me to stop?

345
00:23:32,230 --> 00:23:34,290
我总是说  看好的那边面
I always say, look on the bright side.

346
00:23:34,430 --> 00:23:37,660
在小小的隔离区里  你是知识份子  专业人士
You're in a small ghetto with intellectuals, professional people.

347
00:23:37,800 --> 00:23:39,170
你比我们都更优秀
You're better off than us.

348
00:23:39,300 --> 00:23:41,360
这巨大的隔离区是个烂泥坑
Here in the large ghetto it's a cesspool.

349
00:23:41,510 --> 00:23:42,910
朱哈达  给我点事情做吧
You have to give me something to done.

350
00:23:43,040 --> 00:23:46,100
你是位艺术家  鼓舞人们的灵魂
You're an artist Wladek, you keep peoples' spirits up.

351
00:23:46,250 --> 00:23:46,940
你做得够多了
You do enough.

352
00:23:47,080 --> 00:23:48,710
但我想帮忙  我想做点什么
I want to help, I want to do something.

353
00:23:48,850 --> 00:23:50,640
你太出名了  伙计
You're too well known.buddy

354
00:23:50,780 --> 00:23:52,650
知道吗
you know what?

355
00:23:52,790 --> 00:23:55,850
你们音乐家不是优秀的谋略者
You musicians don't make good conspirators.

356
00:23:55,990 --> 00:23:59,620
你太...太音乐了
You're too... too musical.

357
00:24:06,170 --> 00:24:08,430
-他是谁  -辛契·梅耶克
- Who is that? - Symche.Majorek.

358
00:24:10,670 --> 00:24:13,930
传单满天飞  这城市要清除不受欢迎的人
There are notices going up. City is to be cleansed of the undesirables.

359
00:24:14,070 --> 00:24:17,010
-总是有传单满天飞  -你好  辛契
- There's always notices going up. - Hello, Symche.

360
00:24:18,140 --> 00:24:20,630
你好  多列克  您好  吉丝凯女士
Dyrek. Mrs. Ysken.

361
00:24:23,180 --> 00:24:24,910
裘哈达  工作忙吗
Jehuda, working hard?

362
00:24:25,050 --> 00:24:28,020
梅耶克  这位是波兰最伟大的钢琴家
Majorek, This is the greatest pianist in Poland.

363
00:24:28,150 --> 00:24:29,380
或许也是全世界最棒的
Maybe the whole world.

364
00:24:29,520 --> 00:24:32,320
瓦列迪斯洛·席皮尔曼  见见梅耶克
Wladyslaw Szpilman, meet Majorek.

365
00:24:32,660 --> 00:24:35,350
-你好  -久仰大名
- How do you do? - I know your name.

366
00:24:35,490 --> 00:24:36,760
但未曾听过您演奏
I've never heard you play.

367
00:24:36,900 --> 00:24:39,830
梅耶克一直都在军中  是个出色的男人
Majorek used to be in the Army.Brilliant man.

368
00:24:39,970 --> 00:24:42,870
我唯一与他捍格的是  他不是个社会主义者
The only thing I've got against him is he's not a socialist.

369
00:24:44,900 --> 00:24:47,740
你最好现在离开  瓦列  宵禁时间快到了
You better go now, Wladek. It's nearly curfew.

370
00:24:49,240 --> 00:24:51,470
你知道我们印了几份报纸吗
You know how many copies we print of our newspaper?

371
00:24:52,710 --> 00:24:53,800
500份
Five hundred.

372
00:24:54,480 --> 00:24:57,280
你知道一份报纸平均有几个人传阅吗?
You know how many people on average read one copy?

373
00:24:57,420 --> 00:24:58,110
20人
Twenty.

374
00:24:58,250 --> 00:25:00,910
总共有一万名读者
That makes 10 thousand readers.

375
00:25:01,050 --> 00:25:02,880
这些将为反动催生
This will start the uprising.

376
00:25:03,020 --> 00:25:06,180
梅耶克把它们藏进内裤  然后留在厕所里
Majorek hides them in his underpants and leaves them in toilets.

377
00:25:06,330 --> 00:25:07,020
厕所
Toilets?

378
00:25:07,160 --> 00:25:09,220
所有我找得到的厕所
As many toilets as I can find.

379
00:25:09,360 --> 00:25:11,850
德国人绝不会使用犹太人的厕所
Germans never use Jewish toilets.

380
00:25:12,000 --> 00:25:13,930
对他们而言太干净了嘛
They're too clean for them.

381
00:25:20,540 --> 00:25:23,300
拜托  拜托  帮帮我  先生
Please, mister, please.

382
00:25:50,990 --> 00:25:54,490
别想跑  你个小杂种
Hold it!  You little bastard!

383
00:25:59,750 --> 00:26:01,180
站住  站住
Stop it! Stop it!

384
00:26:02,650 --> 00:26:03,620
站住
Stop it!

385
00:26:06,650 --> 00:26:08,180
快  快  快来
Come on, come on.

386
00:26:08,890 --> 00:26:09,790
来啊  男孩
Come on, boy.

387
00:26:15,660 --> 00:26:18,260
站起来  站起来  站起来
Stand up! Stand up.

388
00:26:19,100 --> 00:26:20,430
站起来  站起来
Stand up! Stand up.

389
00:26:49,700 --> 00:26:54,160
拜托  就今晚这一次  别谈论任何不好的事情
Please, tonight for once, I don't want anything bad talked about.

390
00:26:54,300 --> 00:26:55,600
好好享用这一餐
Enjoy your meal.

391
00:26:55,730 --> 00:26:58,000
好  那么我来说件有趣的事
fine,Then I'll tell you something funny.

392
00:26:58,140 --> 00:26:59,630
你们知道罗席嘉先生吗
You know who I mean by Dr. Raszeja?

393
00:26:59,770 --> 00:27:01,400
-那位军医?  -对 军医
- The surgeon? - The surgeon.

394
00:27:01,540 --> 00:27:03,600
别问我为什么  但因为某个原因
for some reason and not ask me why

395
00:27:03,680 --> 00:27:06,340
德国人允许他到犹太人区做手术
The Germans allowed him into the ghetto to perform an operation.

396
00:27:06,480 --> 00:27:07,600
对犹太人动刀?
On a Jew?

397
00:27:07,680 --> 00:27:09,610
他们让波兰人为犹太人开刀?
They let a Pole to come in to operate on a Jew?

398
00:27:09,750 --> 00:27:13,240
他拿到了通行证  我就知道这些
He got a pass, that's all I know. Anyway, so...

399
00:27:13,390 --> 00:27:15,790
他让病人昏睡过去然后开始动手术
he puts the patient to sleep and starts the operation.

400
00:27:15,920 --> 00:27:18,860
他才刚划下第一刀  SS部队就闯进来
He'd just made the first incision when the SS burst in...

401
00:27:18,990 --> 00:27:21,760
射杀了躺在病床上的病人  然后射杀罗席嘉医生
shoot the patient lie on the table then shoot on Dr. Raszeja

402
00:27:21,890 --> 00:27:23,790
接着是所有在场的人
and everybody else who was there.

403
00:27:25,400 --> 00:27:27,020
这是不是很好笑
Isn't that a laugh?

404
00:27:28,870 --> 00:27:31,500
那病人浑然不觉  因为他被麻醉了
The patient didn't feel a thing, he was anesthetized.

405
00:27:32,370 --> 00:27:34,170
我说过别讲扫兴的事  亨瑞
I said nothing bad.Henryk

406
00:27:34,870 --> 00:27:38,640
你们怎么了  都失去幽默感了吗
What's the matter with you all? You lost your sense of humor?

407
00:27:39,680 --> 00:27:40,580
这不好笑
It's not funny.

408
00:27:41,480 --> 00:27:42,910
你知道什么东西好笑
You know what's funny?

409
00:27:43,050 --> 00:27:45,480
你那条怪里怪气的领带才好笑
You're funny, with that ridiculous tie.

410
00:27:46,290 --> 00:27:49,580
你干嘛讲我的领带  我的领带招谁惹谁了
You talk about my tie for what? What's my tie have to do with anything?

411
00:27:49,690 --> 00:27:51,090
我上班需要这条领带
I need this tie for my work.

412
00:27:51,220 --> 00:27:51,780
你的工作
Your work?

413
00:27:51,920 --> 00:27:52,650
没错  我在工作
That's right, I work.

414
00:27:52,790 --> 00:27:56,420
是啊  弹钢琴给犹太区的那些寄生虫听
Yes,your work. Playing the piano for the parasites in the ghetto.

415
00:27:56,630 --> 00:27:59,320
-寄生虫  -孩子  孩子
- Parasites... - Boys. Boys!

416
00:27:59,460 --> 00:28:01,080
他们对人们所受的苦无动于衷

417
00:28:01,080 --> 00:28:02,300
你因为他们的冷漠谴责我

418
00:28:02,430 --> 00:28:04,060
没错  我每天看着这一切
I do,because I see it everyday.

419
00:28:04,200 --> 00:28:06,300
他们甚至于对发生在周遭的事情无动于衷
They don't even notice what's going around them.

420
00:28:06,440 --> 00:28:07,270
我要谴责美国人
I blame the Americans.

421
00:28:07,410 --> 00:28:08,840
为什么  因为我的领带吗
For what? For my tie?

422
00:28:08,970 --> 00:28:11,470
美国的犹太人  他们在那里人数不少
The American Jews, and there are lots of them.

423
00:28:12,740 --> 00:28:14,710
他们对我们做了什么  他们认为自己在做什么
What do they done? What do they think they're doing?

424
00:28:14,850 --> 00:28:17,910
这里的人因饥饿而亡
People here are dying.Haven't got a bite to eat.

425
00:28:19,280 --> 00:28:23,080
那里的犹太银行家应该督促美国对德国宣战
The Jewish bankers should persuade America to declare war on Germany.

426
00:28:41,010 --> 00:28:41,900
关灯  关灯
The lights! The lights!

427
00:29:01,050 --> 00:29:05,310
开灯

428
00:29:07,980 --> 00:29:10,690
快点

429
00:29:13,570 --> 00:29:17,950
开门  我们要进来

430
00:29:19,820 --> 00:29:21,780
开门

431
00:29:35,590 --> 00:29:37,670
站起来

432
00:29:39,830 --> 00:29:41,090
你

433
00:29:41,700 --> 00:29:42,890
站起来  快点

434
00:29:44,060 --> 00:29:46,640
把他丢出去

435
00:29:58,350 --> 00:30:00,110
嘘  妈妈

436
00:30:00,250 --> 00:30:02,240
喔  我的天
oh,please

437
00:30:02,390 --> 00:30:04,080
喔  我的天
oh,my God

438
00:30:14,380 --> 00:30:17,800
给我跑

439
00:31:24,700 --> 00:31:27,180
不好意思  我是席皮尔曼先生的姐姐

440
00:31:27,180 --> 00:31:28,670
好  进去吧  不是你

441
00:31:48,890 --> 00:31:51,660
-发生什么事  -太可怕了
- What's up? What's up? - It's terrible.

442
00:31:51,660 --> 00:31:52,740
怎么了

443
00:31:52,740 --> 00:31:56,190
他们在街上对人群扫射,他们抓走了亨瑞

444
00:31:58,500 --> 00:31:59,900
你先回家  好吗
Go home, alright?

445
00:32:00,040 --> 00:32:01,530
你先回家  我来处理
Go home,I'll take care of it.

446
00:32:13,120 --> 00:32:14,210
请问一下
Excuse me.

447
00:32:14,350 --> 00:32:16,980
你有看见我丈夫伊沙克  沙曼吗
Have you seen my husband? Izaak Szerman?

448
00:32:17,120 --> 00:32:18,020
恐怕没有
Afraid not.

449
00:32:18,160 --> 00:32:20,950
他高大英俊  蓄着灰色胡子
Tall, handsome, little gray beard.

450
00:32:21,090 --> 00:32:22,560
如果有看见他  请写信通知我
If you see him, write to me.

451
00:32:22,690 --> 00:32:25,060
别忘记  伊沙克  沙曼
Don't forget. Izaak Szerman.

452
00:32:34,770 --> 00:32:36,430
这儿发生了什么事
What happened here?

453
00:32:36,580 --> 00:32:38,480
他们带走了我孙子
They've got my grandson.

454
00:32:38,610 --> 00:32:39,670
他们逮捕了他
They pick them up

455
00:32:39,780 --> 00:32:40,640
他们把他带走了
and take them away.

456
00:32:40,780 --> 00:32:41,970
这些人对他们做了什么
What do they do to them,

457
00:32:42,110 --> 00:32:44,710
我无法再继续信仰上帝
I've stopped believing in God.

458
00:32:45,320 --> 00:32:47,180
不好意思  不好意思
Excuse me. Excuse me.

459
00:32:49,290 --> 00:32:50,250
伊滋查克
Itzak?

460
00:32:51,660 --> 00:32:56,870
伊滋查克  伊滋查克  是我  瓦列·席皮尔曼
Itzak? Itzak, it's Wladek Szpilman.

461
00:33:03,270 --> 00:33:04,630
亨瑞在里面
Henryk is in there.

462
00:33:04,700 --> 00:33:05,670
我没有看见他
I haven't seen him.

463
00:33:05,800 --> 00:33:07,240
相信我  他们逮捕了他
Believe me.They picked him up.

464
00:33:07,370 --> 00:33:08,740
真倒霉

465
00:33:12,340 --> 00:33:13,170
你能帮忙吗
Can you help?

466
00:33:13,310 --> 00:33:15,010
现在你需要我了
Now you need me.

467
00:33:15,150 --> 00:33:16,640
没错  现在你需要我了
Yes,Now you need me!

468
00:33:16,750 --> 00:33:18,480
你能帮助我们吗
Can you help us?

469
00:33:19,580 --> 00:33:20,640
有钱就帮
It costs.

470
00:33:20,720 --> 00:33:22,020
我没钱
I have no money.

471
00:33:22,150 --> 00:33:23,550
那就没有我能效劳之处了
Then there's nothing I can do.

472
00:33:23,690 --> 00:33:25,210
当机会来的时候  你该加入我们的
You should have joined us when you had chance.

473
00:33:25,360 --> 00:33:28,660
伊滋查克  他们告诉我你有影响力
Itzak,They told me you had influence.

474
00:33:28,730 --> 00:33:29,720
谁告诉你的
Who told you?

475
00:33:29,860 --> 00:33:31,160
人们
People

476
00:33:31,300 --> 00:33:34,460
我认识的人  他们说你是有力人士
People I know,They said you're an important man.

477
00:33:36,700 --> 00:33:37,670
伊滋查克
Itzak...

478
00:33:54,390 --> 00:33:57,350
把手举起来

479
00:33:57,560 --> 00:34:02,630
-你好吗  -强盗  砰  砰  去死吧

480
00:34:02,760 --> 00:34:07,070
-去死吧  把手举起来  -他是个疯子

481
00:34:07,280 --> 00:34:10,260
-来一根不  -香烟

482
00:34:10,400 --> 00:34:12,390
嗯  感恩不尽

483
00:34:14,620 --> 00:34:18,580
万事皆安

484
00:34:18,790 --> 00:34:20,920
他看上去可真无忧无虑

485
00:34:21,120 --> 00:34:24,000
万事皆安

486
00:34:24,210 --> 00:34:27,630
万事皆安

487
00:34:28,170 --> 00:34:31,760
举起手来  举起手来

488
00:34:32,260 --> 00:34:33,640
万事皆安

489
00:34:35,460 --> 00:34:37,550
来人啊  帮帮我
Help! Help!

490
00:34:37,700 --> 00:34:39,460
强盗  强盗

491
00:34:39,600 --> 00:34:42,730
来人啊  帮帮我

492
00:35:34,850 --> 00:35:36,050
他们为何逮捕你
Why they picked you up?

493
00:35:36,190 --> 00:35:38,280
你去找了伊滋查克·海勒?
So you go to Itzak Heller?

494
00:35:38,420 --> 00:35:40,550
我有要你去找他吗
Did I ask you to talk to him?

495
00:35:40,630 --> 00:35:42,060
你被放出来了  不是吗
You're out, aren't you?

496
00:35:42,190 --> 00:35:43,590
你求他了吗
Did you beg

497
00:35:43,700 --> 00:35:47,600
-你对那个人渣卑躬屈膝吗  -不  我请他帮助你
- Did you bow to that piece of shit? - I asked him to help you.

498
00:35:47,730 --> 00:35:49,600
你付给他什么报酬
What did you pay him?

499
00:35:50,870 --> 00:35:53,500
我有什么可以给他  拿什么
With what could I pay him? what?

500
00:35:53,640 --> 00:35:55,500
我赚的每分钱都花在食物上了
Every zloty I earn were spend on food.

501
00:35:55,640 --> 00:35:57,470
我可以自己解决
I can look after myself.

502
00:35:57,640 --> 00:35:58,770
他们把你带走了
They were taking you away.

503
00:35:58,910 --> 00:36:00,880
那与你一点关系都没有
It's got nothing to do with you.

504
00:36:01,010 --> 00:36:02,880
他们抓的人是我  不是你
It's me they wanted, not you.

505
00:36:03,010 --> 00:36:06,420
你为什么一定要干涉别人的事情
Why do you have to interfere with other people's business?

506
00:36:06,550 --> 00:36:08,610
你疯了  你的麻烦就是你疯了
You're mad. That's your trouble.You are mad.

507
00:36:08,690 --> 00:36:10,710
那也是我的事
That's also my business.

508
00:36:16,960 --> 00:36:21,400
怎么了
hey,what's the matter?

509
00:36:21,530 --> 00:36:23,430
怎么了  你病了吗
What's the matter? Are you sick?

510
00:36:24,400 --> 00:36:25,330
饿了
Hungry.

511
00:36:33,910 --> 00:36:35,540
就业许可证?
Employment certificate.

512
00:36:36,080 --> 00:36:38,340
什么意思  没有就业许可证会怎样
What's that mean, no employment certificate?

513
00:36:38,480 --> 00:36:40,820
你必需要有就业许可证
You have to have an employment certificate...

514
00:36:42,020 --> 00:36:44,150
才能在犹太区的德属公司工作  否则...
to work for the Germans firms in the ghetto, otherwise...

515
00:36:44,290 --> 00:36:45,590
否则怎样
Otherwise what?

516
00:36:45,720 --> 00:36:47,020
你会被驱逐
You'll be deported.

517
00:36:47,160 --> 00:36:49,060
那么谣传是真的了
So the rumors were true.

518
00:36:49,190 --> 00:36:51,590
他们要重新处置我们
They're going to resettle us...

519
00:36:51,660 --> 00:36:54,390
把我们送到东边的集中营
and send us to labor camps, in the East.

520
00:36:56,670 --> 00:36:57,970
然后他们要关闭这个小犹太区
They're closing the small ghetto.

521
00:36:58,100 --> 00:36:59,260
我的天
Oh, God!

522
00:37:15,020 --> 00:37:16,950
瓦列  瓦列
Wladek? Wladek?

523
00:37:18,060 --> 00:37:19,410
我以为你会到伦敦
I thought you were on tour playing in London,

524
00:37:19,410 --> 00:37:21,820
巴黎  纽约  芝加哥巡回演出
 Paris, New York, Chicago.

525
00:37:21,960 --> 00:37:22,760
不是这个礼拜
Not this week.

526
00:37:22,890 --> 00:37:24,090
你看起来很糟
You look terrible.

527
00:37:24,960 --> 00:37:26,360
你有听到谣传吗
Have you heard the rumors?

528
00:37:26,500 --> 00:37:28,190
他们要把我们重新安置在东部
They're going to resettle us in the East.

529
00:37:28,330 --> 00:37:30,930
谣传  你太把它们当一回事了
Rumors! You take it all too much to heart.Wladek

530
00:37:31,070 --> 00:37:32,470
有什么麻烦吗
What's the trouble?

531
00:37:32,670 --> 00:37:37,000
我一直试着帮我父亲申请一张工作许可证
I've been trying to get the certificate of employment for my father.

532
00:37:37,140 --> 00:37:39,130
我已经设法帮我自己和我其他家人找到了
I managed to get one for me and the rest of my family,

533
00:37:39,280 --> 00:37:40,870
但我还需要另外一张给我父亲
but I need another one for my father.

534
00:37:41,010 --> 00:37:42,070
我已经跑遍所有公司和商店
I've been to all the firms and shops...

535
00:37:42,210 --> 00:37:44,180
你为什么不来找我呢
Why didn't you come to me?

536
00:37:44,320 --> 00:37:46,250
我不知道你在处理许可证的业务
I didn't know you were in the certificate business.

537
00:37:46,380 --> 00:37:48,580
不是我  是梅耶克
I'm not, but Majorek is.

538
00:37:51,160 --> 00:37:53,120
你能帮忙吗  但我没钱
Can you help? I have no money.

539
00:37:53,260 --> 00:37:56,920
-拜托  别贬低我们  -你可以为他做点什么吗
- Please, don't insult us. -Can you do something for him?

540
00:37:57,060 --> 00:37:59,790
明天四点到修兹工作室
Be at the Schultz workshop tomorrow, four o'clock.

541
00:37:59,930 --> 00:38:02,700
瞧你今天运气有多好
See what a wonderful piece of luck you've had today?

542
00:38:02,830 --> 00:38:05,360
命中注定啊
That's the historical imperative in action!

543
00:38:05,500 --> 00:38:07,490
那就是我常说的 要看光明面
That's why I always say "Look on the bright side!"

544
00:38:07,640 --> 00:38:09,130
光明面  是  我知道
The bright side,Yes, I know.

545
00:38:22,390 --> 00:38:23,720
你的背怎样了
How's your back?

546
00:38:23,860 --> 00:38:24,980
好多了
Better.

547
00:38:25,120 --> 00:38:27,180
好多了吗
Better?

548
00:38:27,330 --> 00:38:29,320
已经好多了
Better than ask

549
00:38:42,370 --> 00:38:43,430
谢谢你
Thank you.

550
00:38:44,040 --> 00:38:47,570
不客气  虽然我什么忙也帮不上
My pleasure. Won't help you anyway.

551
00:38:50,010 --> 00:38:51,410
谢谢你  修兹先生
Thank you, Mr. Schultz.

552
00:39:04,630 --> 00:39:07,430
1942年3月15日

553
00:40:03,290 --> 00:40:06,420
至少我们在犹太区找到工作了
At least we got work in the ghetto.

554
00:40:07,390 --> 00:40:09,020
至少我们都还在一起
At least we are still together.

555
00:40:23,880 --> 00:40:24,740
全部出去

556
00:40:24,880 --> 00:40:26,430
到院子去

557
00:40:26,610 --> 00:40:28,990
别站着不动

558
00:40:29,610 --> 00:40:31,140
我们都是雇员

559
00:40:31,280 --> 00:40:33,580
我们有工作证

560
00:40:37,750 --> 00:40:39,880
等等
Wait.

561
00:40:40,630 --> 00:40:41,630
给你
Here.

562
00:40:41,920 --> 00:40:45,050
去那里  快点

563
00:40:45,130 --> 00:40:46,100
你

564
00:40:47,770 --> 00:40:49,530
你  你

565
00:40:52,100 --> 00:40:53,200
你

566
00:40:55,740 --> 00:40:56,470
你

567
00:40:59,110 --> 00:41:00,270
你

568
00:41:10,020 --> 00:41:12,960
其余的人穿好衣服回到这里

569
00:41:13,690 --> 00:41:16,060
带着你们的东西  最多15公斤

570
00:41:16,990 --> 00:41:19,220
您要把我们送去哪里

571
00:41:43,820 --> 00:41:45,450
抱歉  我已经尽力了
I'm sorry, I did my best.

572
00:41:48,660 --> 00:41:50,460
我以为工作证可以拯救我们
I thought the certificates'd save us.

573
00:41:50,660 --> 00:41:51,650
别说了  瓦列
Stop it, Wladek.

574
00:41:51,800 --> 00:41:55,320
就让我们一心期望亨瑞和哈琳娜安然无恙
Let's just hope that Henryk and Halina will be better off.

575
00:41:58,400 --> 00:42:00,890
1942年8月16日

576
00:42:22,960 --> 00:42:24,260
我们要到哪里去
Where will we be going?

577
00:42:24,400 --> 00:42:25,520
你们要去工作
Going to work.

578
00:42:25,700 --> 00:42:28,890
你们会比待在那个臭气熏天的犹太区好多了  向前走
You'll be much better off than in the stinking ghetto. Move.

579
00:42:33,540 --> 00:42:35,010
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

580
00:42:35,870 --> 00:42:37,360
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

581
00:42:38,580 --> 00:42:40,070
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

582
00:42:41,780 --> 00:42:43,610
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

583
00:42:45,180 --> 00:42:47,240
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

584
00:42:52,060 --> 00:42:53,920
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

585
00:42:54,060 --> 00:42:57,820
我怎能这样做  我怎能这样做
Why did I do it? Why did I do it?

586
00:43:00,100 --> 00:43:01,720
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

587
00:43:03,370 --> 00:43:05,960
我怎能这样做
Why did I do it?

588
00:43:31,900 --> 00:43:33,800
你有水吗
Don't you have a bottle of water?

589
00:43:33,930 --> 00:43:36,730
他快死了  我的孩子快要渴死了
He's dying.My child is dying of thirst.

590
00:43:36,870 --> 00:43:38,700
-我求求你  求求你  -我很抱歉
- I beg you.I beg you. - I'm sorry.

591
00:43:38,840 --> 00:43:41,600
你有水吗  求求你
Don't you have a bottle of water? I beg you.

592
00:43:41,670 --> 00:43:42,830
你听到我说的话吗
Did you hear what I'm saying?

593
00:43:42,970 --> 00:43:44,500
我告诉你  这是一个耻辱
I'm telling you, it's a disgrace.

594
00:43:44,640 --> 00:43:45,200
我在听
I can hear you.

595
00:43:45,340 --> 00:43:47,710
我们任凭他们把我们引向死亡  就像羔羊走向屠场
Letting them take us to our death like sheep to the slaughter.

596
00:43:47,850 --> 00:43:48,710
别这么大声
Not so loud.

597
00:43:48,850 --> 00:43:50,070
我们何不反击
Why don't we attack them?

598
00:43:50,210 --> 00:43:53,510
我们有五十万人在这里  我们可以突破犹太区重围
There's half a million of us here. We can break out of the ghetto.

599
00:43:53,650 --> 00:43:54,970
至少我们可以光荣地死去
At least we can die honorably,

600
00:43:54,980 --> 00:43:56,420
而不是当历史上的一个污点
not as a stain on the face of History.

601
00:43:56,550 --> 00:43:57,450
为何你这么确定
Why are you so sure

602
00:43:57,660 --> 00:43:58,620
他们会送我们下黄泉
they're sending us to our death?

603
00:43:58,690 --> 00:43:59,620
我不确定
I'm not sure

604
00:43:59,720 --> 00:44:00,660
你知道为什么我不能确定吗
You know why I'm not sure?

605
00:44:00,790 --> 00:44:02,820
他们又没告诉我
Because they didn't tell me.

606
00:44:02,960 --> 00:44:04,700
他们要把我们赶尽杀绝

607
00:44:04,700 --> 00:44:06,860
你希望我怎么做  你要我抗争吗

608
00:44:07,000 --> 00:44:09,130
抗争的话需要组织  计划  枪支...
To fight, we need organization, plans, guns.

609
00:44:09,270 --> 00:44:10,460
他说得没错  你认为我能做什么
He's right. Do you think I'm going

610
00:44:10,670 --> 00:44:12,230
用我的小提琴弓抗争吗
to fight with my violin bowl?

611
00:44:12,370 --> 00:44:15,740
德国人不会浪费像这样庞大的劳力
The Germans would never squander a huge labor force like this.

612
00:44:15,870 --> 00:44:17,740
很明显地他们正要把我们送到集中营
They're sending us to a labor camp,

613
00:44:17,880 --> 00:44:20,540
喔 当然  看看那个瘸子
oh,Sure. Look at that cripple there,

614
00:44:20,980 --> 00:44:24,040
看看这些老人跟小孩  他们也要工作吗
the old people, the children. They're going to work?

615
00:44:24,180 --> 00:44:27,840
看看你  你要带着背上的铁架一起去吗
Look at you. You're going to carry logs on your back?

616
00:45:10,060 --> 00:45:11,430
亨瑞
Henryk!

617
00:45:11,560 --> 00:45:13,260
哈莲娜  亨瑞
Halina, Henryk!

618
00:45:13,400 --> 00:45:15,390
哈莲娜  亨瑞
Halina, Henryk!

619
00:45:22,770 --> 00:45:25,070
我们听说你们在这里

620
00:45:25,210 --> 00:45:27,640
我们要跟你们在一起
I wanted to be with you!

621
00:45:36,120 --> 00:45:38,150
我们要跟你们在一起
I wanted to be with you!

622
00:45:38,290 --> 00:45:41,320
笨蛋  笨蛋
Stupid. Stupid.

623
00:45:41,460 --> 00:45:46,060
我怎能这样做  我怎能这样做
Why did I do it? Why did I do it?

624
00:45:46,200 --> 00:45:48,690
她让我神经紧张
She's getting on my nerves.

625
00:45:53,340 --> 00:45:55,930
老天爷  她到底做了什么
What did she do, for God's sake?

626
00:45:56,070 --> 00:45:57,730
她闷死了她的婴儿
She smothered her baby.

627
00:46:00,440 --> 00:46:04,110
他们准备了一个隐匿处  他们都躲在那里
They prepared a hiding place and of course they went there.

628
00:46:04,250 --> 00:46:06,980
但是当警察来的时候  婴儿哭了起来
The baby cried just as the police came.

629
00:46:07,120 --> 00:46:09,810
她用手捂住啼哭的婴儿
She smothered the cries with her hands,

630
00:46:09,950 --> 00:46:11,790
婴儿就这么死了
the baby died.

631
00:46:12,660 --> 00:46:14,180
有个警察听见了声响
A policeman heard the death rattle

632
00:46:14,330 --> 00:46:16,350
发现他们的藏身之处
and found where they were hiding.

633
00:46:27,670 --> 00:46:32,340
妈妈
mama

634
00:46:41,520 --> 00:46:42,680
你在读什么
What are you reading?

635
00:46:46,320 --> 00:46:48,420
若你戳刺我们  我们不会流血吗
"If you prick us, de we not bleed?

636
00:46:48,630 --> 00:46:50,590
若你呵我们痒  我们不会发笑吗
If you tickle us, do we not laugh?

637
00:46:51,300 --> 00:46:53,260
若你对我们下毒  我们不会死去吗
If you poison us, do we not die?

638
00:46:53,400 --> 00:46:56,300
若你加害于我们  我们不应该复仇吗
And, if you wrong us,shall we not revenge?"

639
00:47:04,640 --> 00:47:05,900
写得很好
Very appropriate.

640
00:47:06,040 --> 00:47:07,600
是啊  这就是我带着它的原因
Yes. That's why I brought it.

641
00:47:25,960 --> 00:47:28,630
那个傻瓜  他觉得在这儿赚钱还有用吗
Idiot. What does he think he's gonna do with the money?

642
00:47:30,670 --> 00:47:31,530
嘿  男孩
Boy,

643
00:47:31,670 --> 00:47:32,900
来这里
come here.

644
00:47:34,210 --> 00:47:35,190
来这里
Come here.

645
00:47:37,210 --> 00:47:38,230
一块奶糖要多少钱
How much for a caramel?

646
00:47:38,380 --> 00:47:39,670
20波币
20 zlotys.

647
00:47:39,810 --> 00:47:41,000
什么  一块奶糖要要这么多
What? For one caramel?

648
00:47:41,150 --> 00:47:42,740
你想要怎么花这些钱
What do you think you're gonna do with the money?

649
00:47:42,880 --> 00:47:44,610
20波币
20 zlotys.

650
00:47:46,880 --> 00:47:48,250
我们谁有20波币吗
We've got 20 between us.

651
00:47:49,290 --> 00:47:50,580
我想我有10元
I've got 10, I think.

652
00:47:54,630 --> 00:47:56,960
5  10  20
5, 10, 20.

653
00:49:20,150 --> 00:49:21,780
-哈琳娜  -什么
- Halina? - What?

654
00:49:24,290 --> 00:49:26,590
现在说这个挺怪的  但是...
It's a funny time to say this, but...

655
00:49:26,730 --> 00:49:27,790
什么
What?

656
00:49:29,360 --> 00:49:31,330
但愿我能多了解你一些
I wish I knew you better.

657
00:49:35,640 --> 00:49:36,830
谢谢
Thank you.

658
00:49:53,990 --> 00:49:55,080
席皮尔曼
Szpilman

659
00:49:55,990 --> 00:49:56,920
席皮尔曼
Szpilman

660
00:50:01,930 --> 00:50:04,760
滚开  笨蛋  走

661
00:50:05,500 --> 00:50:07,590
爸爸  爸爸
Papa? Papa?

662
00:50:08,640 --> 00:50:09,430
爸爸
papa

663
00:50:10,370 --> 00:50:11,700
妈妈  哈琳娜
Mama? Halina?

664
00:50:13,240 --> 00:50:14,900
哈琳娜  妈妈
Halina? Mama?

665
00:50:16,180 --> 00:50:17,770
你以为自己在干嘛  席皮尔曼
What do you think you're doing,Szpilman?

666
00:50:17,910 --> 00:50:18,810
我救了你一命
I saved your life.

667
00:50:18,950 --> 00:50:21,380
起来  快走  走
Just get up,go! Go!

668
00:50:25,120 --> 00:50:26,090
别用跑的
Don't run!

669
00:50:29,090 --> 00:50:33,920
安娜  安娜  安娜
Anna!Anna!Anna!

670
00:50:53,150 --> 00:50:56,340
好  把他们送去彻底改造

671
00:50:56,480 --> 00:50:57,470
是的

672
00:50:59,290 --> 00:51:04,040
这个留下  把它给我

673
00:51:09,460 --> 00:51:11,590
你在干什么  她是孕妇
What are you doing? She's pregnant.

674
00:51:47,600 --> 00:51:49,070
向左转

675
00:51:55,610 --> 00:51:56,770
齐步走

676
00:53:39,080 --> 00:53:40,510
瓦列
Wladek?

677
00:53:59,270 --> 00:54:01,030
你怎么会在这里  瓦列
Why are you here, Wladek?

678
00:54:02,470 --> 00:54:05,170
就是这样  我  我
It's like this, I...

679
00:54:06,840 --> 00:54:08,100
我们...
We...

680
00:54:11,080 --> 00:54:13,710
他们所有人  他们所有人
All of them, all of them.

681
00:54:14,480 --> 00:54:15,850
他们所有人
All of them.

682
00:54:17,750 --> 00:54:20,480
也许他们够幸运  早登极乐
Perhaps they're lucky. The quicker, the better.

683
00:54:21,860 --> 00:54:24,850
现在还没有结束  我们将在这里待上些日子
It's not finished yet. We'll stay here for a couple of days...

684
00:54:24,990 --> 00:54:27,020
直到尘埃落定
until things die down.

685
00:54:27,160 --> 00:54:30,620
我已经贿赂了一个警察  事情结束的时候他会过来
I've bribed the policeman, he'll come when it's over.

686
00:54:32,880 --> 00:54:36,630
立正  前进

687
00:54:46,640 --> 00:54:48,600
跟上

688
00:54:51,120 --> 00:54:53,950
天呐  我已经有二年没有出去过了
My God, I haven't been outside in, it must be two years.

689
00:54:54,490 --> 00:54:55,820
真激动
Don't get overexcited.

690
00:55:13,110 --> 00:55:14,300
黄金
gold.

691
00:55:15,240 --> 00:55:16,710
这价钱很好
Very good price.

692
00:55:37,630 --> 00:55:38,720
有认识的人吗
Someone you know?

693
00:55:39,930 --> 00:55:41,530
这个美人是谁
A beauty. Who is she?

694
00:55:41,940 --> 00:55:44,530
她是个歌手  事实上我跟她很熟
She's a singer. I knew her well.

695
00:55:44,670 --> 00:55:46,200
她丈夫是演员
Her husband is an actor.

696
00:55:46,340 --> 00:55:47,830
他们都是好人
They're good people.

697
00:55:47,980 --> 00:55:48,770
我想跟她说话
I'd like to talk to her.

698
00:55:48,910 --> 00:55:52,180
别忘记  支援犹太人的都被绞死了
Don't forget, Wladek.They hang them for helping Jews.

699
00:56:19,530 --> 00:56:21,950
向左转

700
00:56:22,110 --> 00:56:24,610
前进

701
00:56:28,790 --> 00:56:31,580
立正

702
00:56:46,000 --> 00:56:47,520
向右转

703
00:56:55,900 --> 00:56:58,610
出列

704
00:56:59,150 --> 00:57:00,730
你

705
00:57:02,990 --> 00:57:05,570
你

706
00:57:06,280 --> 00:57:08,120
你

707
00:57:12,080 --> 00:57:14,160
趴下

708
00:57:14,330 --> 00:57:17,500
趴下

709
00:57:44,780 --> 00:57:46,910
向右转

710
00:57:48,070 --> 00:57:50,530
前进

711
00:58:30,670 --> 00:58:31,870
你在这里待多久了
How long have you been here?

712
00:58:33,240 --> 00:58:34,570
昨晚开始的
Since last night.

713
00:58:36,380 --> 00:58:37,570
很高兴遇见你
I was pleased to see you.

714
00:58:42,650 --> 00:58:44,410
他们现在即将开始进行最后的安置
They're going to start the final resettlement now.

715
00:58:47,820 --> 00:58:49,050
我们知道那意味着什么
We know what it means.

716
00:58:51,290 --> 00:58:54,730
我们送了一个人出去  席格蒙  他是个好人
We sent someone out. Zygmund, a good man.

717
00:58:57,800 --> 00:58:59,660
他受命追踪从华沙发出的列车
His orders were to follow the trains out of Warsaw.

718
00:59:02,570 --> 00:59:03,700
他抵达索克洛
He got to Sokolow.

719
00:59:04,870 --> 00:59:07,310
一位当地的铁道员告诉他  轨道在那里分歧了
A man told him the tracks divided,

720
00:59:07,780 --> 00:59:09,270
一条通往催布林卡
one branch's leading to Treblinka.

721
00:59:11,580 --> 00:59:15,410
他说每天运货列车载着满车的人从华沙驶来
He said everyday freight trains carrying people from Warsaw...

722
00:59:15,580 --> 00:59:18,680
开往催布林卡的方向  然后空车返回
branch off to Treblinka and return empty.

723
00:59:19,750 --> 00:59:21,850
在那条路线上  从没看过有食物运送
No transports of food are ever seen on that line.

724
00:59:23,490 --> 00:59:27,050
而居民...被禁止靠近催布林卡车站
The civilians are forbidden to approach the Treblinka station.

725
00:59:31,070 --> 00:59:32,430
他们想把我们赶尽杀绝
They're exterminating us.

726
00:59:37,240 --> 00:59:39,930
那用不着花太多时间
It won't take them long.

727
00:59:41,240 --> 00:59:44,010
从50万人到现在  我们只剩下6万人
We are 60 thousand left, out of half a million.

728
00:59:45,650 --> 00:59:47,010
几乎都是年轻人
Mostly young people.

729
00:59:49,550 --> 00:59:51,020
而这一次我们要反抗
And this time we're gonna fight.

730
00:59:54,360 --> 00:59:58,160
我们状况良好  组织健全
We're in good shape.Organized.

731
00:59:59,390 --> 01:00:00,690
我们已经准备好了
We're prepared.

732
01:00:01,460 --> 01:00:02,900
如果你需要援助  我...
If you need help, I...

733
01:00:23,420 --> 01:00:26,250
你  过来
You! Come here!

734
01:00:27,890 --> 01:00:29,410
喔  可恶  可恶
Shit!

735
01:00:38,070 --> 01:00:40,400
抱歉  我很抱歉
sorry.I'm sorry.

736
01:00:40,530 --> 01:00:43,160
我...我刚刚失了神
I don't know what I was thinking.

737
01:00:46,810 --> 01:00:49,830
不  拜托  不要  拜托
please, please

738
01:00:49,980 --> 01:00:52,000
拜托
please

739
01:01:12,000 --> 01:01:13,000
把他拖走

740
01:01:30,550 --> 01:01:33,490
我希望你弹钢琴的功夫比砌砖好
I hope you play the piano better than you carry bricks.

741
01:01:36,320 --> 01:01:38,420
他不会撑太久的  如果他继续这样下去
He won't last long if he goes on like this.

742
01:01:39,060 --> 01:01:41,550
我看看我是否能让他好过一点
I'll see if I can get him something better.

743
01:02:04,420 --> 01:02:05,650
有麻烦
Trouble.

744
01:02:09,190 --> 01:02:12,320
集合  只有犹太人
Round up! Only the Jews.

745
01:02:12,460 --> 01:02:15,620
波兰人继续干活  犹太人集合
The Polish keep working. Only the Jews.

746
01:02:23,300 --> 01:02:25,100
我有好消息要告诉你们
I have good news for you.

747
01:02:26,070 --> 01:02:28,670
到处都有谣言...
There are rumors going around that

748
01:02:29,180 --> 01:02:32,630
我们就要  呃...
we like to

749
01:02:32,780 --> 01:02:34,510
安置你们
to resettle you.

750
01:02:36,380 --> 01:02:41,320
我保证  从今以后
I promise you that now and in the future...

751
01:02:41,460 --> 01:02:43,890
再也没有新计划
nothing else is planned.

752
01:02:47,190 --> 01:02:48,860
基于这个原因
For this reason,

753
01:02:49,000 --> 01:02:53,660
我们要在墙上贴公报
we put information posters on the wall.

754
01:02:53,800 --> 01:02:57,200
为了表示我们的善意
To show you our goodwill...

755
01:02:57,340 --> 01:02:59,640
应该推举你们当中某一个人...
you should vote one of you to be allowed...

756
01:02:59,770 --> 01:03:04,710
他获准每天进城...
to go in town daily...

757
01:03:04,850 --> 01:03:11,250
带回三公斤的马铃薯...
and bring 3 kilos of potatoes...

758
01:03:11,390 --> 01:03:13,620
还有一条面包...
and one loaf of bread

759
01:03:13,750 --> 01:03:15,720
给你们每一个工人
for each of your workers.

760
01:03:15,860 --> 01:03:19,590
如果我们要把你们怎么样的话
So, why should we do something like this

761
01:03:19,690 --> 01:03:22,590
我们为何还要这样做呢
if we'd resettle you?

762
01:03:22,700 --> 01:03:25,190
你们可以好好做生意...
You can make good business

763
01:03:25,330 --> 01:03:29,130
不做这一行  你们会没饭吃
out of the things you don't eat.

764
01:03:29,270 --> 01:03:33,230
这不是是你们犹太人最擅长的吗
Isn't that something that you Jews are good in?

765
01:03:33,370 --> 01:03:35,100
赚钱
Making money?

766
01:03:39,250 --> 01:03:40,410
回去工作

767
01:03:56,700 --> 01:03:58,690
那个...是用绳子绑的
That one, with the string.

768
01:03:58,830 --> 01:04:00,560
其它的用铁线绑
The others, tied by wire.

769
01:05:09,370 --> 01:05:10,390
现在
Now!

770
01:05:48,110 --> 01:05:49,410
梅耶克
Majorek.

771
01:05:51,850 --> 01:05:53,440
我想请你帮我一个忙
I have a favor to ask.

772
01:05:55,220 --> 01:05:56,940
我想要离开这里
I want to get out of here.

773
01:06:00,620 --> 01:06:02,150
要出去很容易
It's easy to get out.

774
01:06:03,160 --> 01:06:05,020
困难的是你要如何在外面存活下来
It's how you survive on the other side,that's hard.

775
01:06:05,160 --> 01:06:08,030
我明白  我明白
I know.I know.

776
01:06:08,160 --> 01:06:09,890
去年夏天
Last summer,I worked for a day

777
01:06:10,030 --> 01:06:12,360
我曾在兹兰那 布拉马广场工作了一天
in the Zelazna Brama Square.

778
01:06:12,500 --> 01:06:15,870
我看见一个认识的人  她是个老朋友了
I saw someone I knew, she's an old friend.

779
01:06:16,000 --> 01:06:19,200
一位歌手  她丈夫是个演员
A singer, her husband is an actor.

780
01:06:21,110 --> 01:06:23,440
我写下他们的名字跟地址
I've filled their names down and their address,

781
01:06:23,610 --> 01:06:25,200
如果他们还住在原处的话
if they're still there.

782
01:06:25,350 --> 01:06:28,210
嘉琳娜·果朵瓦丝卡和安德兹·博克基
Janina Godlewska and Andrzej Bogucki.

783
01:06:28,350 --> 01:06:30,410
他们都是好人
They're good people.

784
01:06:30,880 --> 01:06:33,050
你能试着连络上他们吗
Would you try to make contact?

785
01:06:35,320 --> 01:06:38,450
你每天都进城  你能问问他们...
You go to town everyday, would you just ask them...

786
01:06:38,630 --> 01:06:41,320
问他们是否能帮我逃离这里
Ask them if they'd help me get out of here.

787
01:07:14,090 --> 01:07:16,190
有药膏吗

788
01:07:25,970 --> 01:07:28,070
你上来做什么

789
01:07:31,040 --> 01:07:32,570
里面是什么

790
01:07:33,710 --> 01:07:36,880
我们获准把食物带进犹太区

791
01:07:37,880 --> 01:07:40,180
3公斤的马铃薯和面包

792
01:07:40,920 --> 01:07:41,850
打开

793
01:07:46,290 --> 01:07:48,320
马铃薯和面包

794
01:07:48,460 --> 01:07:51,520
你在说谎  我嗅到你的谎言了

795
01:07:53,090 --> 01:07:55,260
打开

796
01:08:23,430 --> 01:08:25,090
马铃薯?

797
01:08:29,200 --> 01:08:32,000
你们犹太人都一样

798
01:08:32,140 --> 01:08:33,870
你们犹太人...

799
01:08:34,010 --> 01:08:35,800
...总是

800
01:08:35,940 --> 01:08:38,570
得寸进尺

801
01:08:52,430 --> 01:08:55,050
下次再骗我  我就把你给毙了

802
01:08:55,200 --> 01:08:56,590
我以名义起誓

803
01:09:20,820 --> 01:09:22,850
我试着去找你的朋友
I tried your friends.

804
01:09:22,990 --> 01:09:24,150
他们没有住在那里了
They don't live there anymore.

805
01:09:24,290 --> 01:09:26,230
那...你联络到了吗
Did you make contact?

806
01:09:27,460 --> 01:09:28,690
你可以准备离开了
Be ready to leave.

807
01:09:28,830 --> 01:09:29,590
何时
When?

808
01:09:29,730 --> 01:09:30,460
尽快
Soon.

809
01:09:30,600 --> 01:09:31,790
立定
Halt!

810
01:09:35,430 --> 01:09:38,030
我们要去哪儿

811
01:09:48,420 --> 01:09:51,650
我教你们什么叫纪律  犹太猪

812
01:09:56,760 --> 01:09:59,120
知道为什么要扁你们吗

813
01:09:59,260 --> 01:09:59,880
-不  -知道为什么要扁你们吗

814
01:10:02,600 --> 01:10:03,690
为什么

815
01:10:03,830 --> 01:10:06,030
为了庆祝耶诞夜

816
01:10:09,500 --> 01:10:11,840
现在  前进

817
01:10:11,900 --> 01:10:14,500
前进  把歌唱起来

818
01:10:15,010 --> 01:10:16,600
唱点让人振奋的歌

819
01:10:17,610 --> 01:10:20,410
大声地唱  整齐地唱

820
01:11:19,630 --> 01:11:21,680
走

821
01:12:36,450 --> 01:12:40,410
对不起  我脏兮兮的
I'm sorry.I'm dirty. I'm so filthy.

822
01:13:06,210 --> 01:13:07,940
我们没有太多时间  来吧
We haven't much time.Come on.

823
01:13:16,620 --> 01:13:17,650
我们得快一点
We must hurry.

824
01:13:18,760 --> 01:13:20,450
这里  看看合不合身
Here. See if this fit.

825
01:13:21,630 --> 01:13:22,790
我们得一直换地方
We have to keep moving

826
01:13:22,930 --> 01:13:25,400
德国人现在不分青红皂白地搜捕
Germans are hunting down indiscriminately now.

827
01:13:25,530 --> 01:13:28,500
犹太人  非犹太人  任何人  每一个人
Jews, non-Jews, anybody, everybody.

828
01:13:28,970 --> 01:13:31,270
瓦列  你最好刮一下胡子
Wladek,You better shave.

829
01:13:31,400 --> 01:13:32,930
用我架子上的刮胡刀
Use my razor on the shelf.

830
01:13:47,850 --> 01:13:50,080
马里克 吉勃克辛斯基会照顾你的
You'll be looked after by Gebczynski.

831
01:13:50,790 --> 01:13:52,220
他住在城的另一边
He's on the other side of town.

832
01:13:53,090 --> 01:13:55,760
今晚你就待在那里  我们会再帮你找新的住处
You stay there tonight, then we'll find you somewhere else.

833
01:13:57,600 --> 01:13:59,120
我会带食物给你
I'll bring you food.

834
01:13:59,970 --> 01:14:01,160
好吧  我们走了
Alright, let's go.

835
01:14:41,210 --> 01:14:43,070
我会告诉你要睡在哪里
I'll show you where you're going to sleep.

836
01:15:14,610 --> 01:15:17,240
你必需在这边待到明天下午
You have to stay here until tomorrow afternoon.

837
01:15:17,740 --> 01:15:21,040
我们在犹太区围墙附近为你准备了公寓
We have a flat for you near the ghetto wall.

838
01:15:21,180 --> 01:15:22,340
不过那里很安全
But it's safe.

839
01:15:29,920 --> 01:15:32,360
这里不太舒适
It's not going to be very comfortable.

840
01:15:32,930 --> 01:15:34,260
已经很好了
I'll be fine.

841
01:15:44,640 --> 01:15:45,830
谢谢你
Thank you.

842
01:16:02,620 --> 01:16:04,560
我来拿  给我
Here. Here. Give it to me.

843
01:16:05,990 --> 01:16:08,790
仅可能往前坐 靠近德国区
Go as near to the front as possible,to the German section.

844
01:16:28,150 --> 01:16:29,940
请勿穿过

845
01:17:01,180 --> 01:17:02,610
我现在要拉下窗帘
I'm going to draw the curtains now.

846
01:17:09,190 --> 01:17:11,050
但你整个白天要任由它们敞开着
But you leave them open during the day.

847
01:17:11,190 --> 01:17:12,560
不要忘记
Don't forget.

848
01:17:15,830 --> 01:17:18,460
在墙的这一边一定会好过些吧
Must feel better on this side of the wall,eh?

849
01:17:19,270 --> 01:17:20,560
是
Yes.

850
01:17:22,270 --> 01:17:25,570
但有时候我仍不确定自己是在墙的哪一边
But sometimes I'm still not sure which side of the wall I'm on.

851
01:17:28,610 --> 01:17:31,700
这儿有些面包... 马铃薯 洋葱
Some bread,potatoes,onions.

852
01:17:32,410 --> 01:17:33,570
我会再来的
I'll come again.

853
01:17:33,710 --> 01:17:35,940
还有妮娜·博嘉琪  每周会来看你二次
Janina will visit you twice a week.

854
01:17:36,080 --> 01:17:38,240
给你带更多食物  看看你好不好
bring more food,see how you are.

855
01:17:38,950 --> 01:17:40,080
谢谢
Thank you.

856
01:17:42,090 --> 01:17:44,520
这个非常重要
This is very important.

857
01:17:45,390 --> 01:17:48,190
如果万一发生紧急状况... 我是说非常紧急...
In case of emergency...I mean emergency,

858
01:17:48,800 --> 01:17:50,160
到这个地址去
go to this address.

859
01:18:33,770 --> 01:18:36,070
混蛋  你说忘记是什么意思
Fuck you dog,what do you mean you forgot?

860
01:18:36,210 --> 01:18:37,900
你认为我是什么意思
What do you think I mean?

861
01:18:38,040 --> 01:18:39,340
我的意思就是我忘记了
I forgot,that's what I mean.

862
01:18:39,480 --> 01:18:41,610
你待我如粪土 .
You know what,you treat me like dirt.

863
01:18:41,750 --> 01:18:44,810
我待你如粪土  因为你就是粪土
Treat you like dirt? Because you are a dirt.

864
01:18:44,950 --> 01:18:47,110
猪头  猪头
Pig! Pig!

865
01:18:47,250 --> 01:18:50,550
-婊子  你是只肮脏的猪猡
- Bitch!You are a dirty pig!

866
01:18:50,690 --> 01:18:53,520
彼此彼此  猪头
Takes one to know one. Pig.

867
01:18:57,760 --> 01:18:59,890
你弹琴时像个天使
Um,you play like an angel,catskin.

868
01:19:00,030 --> 01:19:02,520
如果我弹琴像个天使  你为什么不听
If i look like an angel,why don't you listen?

869
01:19:02,640 --> 01:19:03,930
我有听啊  小喵咪
I'm listening.

870
01:19:04,070 --> 01:19:06,600
骗子  你明明睡着了  小猪头
Liar.You fell asleep. Pig.

871
01:19:17,580 --> 01:19:20,180
1943年4月19日

872
01:19:29,790 --> 01:19:33,840
散开  我们遭到袭击了

873
01:19:36,340 --> 01:19:38,760
藏起来

874
01:19:40,430 --> 01:19:41,430
射击

875
01:19:53,520 --> 01:19:56,400
隐蔽  开火

876
01:20:00,570 --> 01:20:03,370
快点  跑呀

877
01:20:24,120 --> 01:20:25,580
射击  射击
fire!fire!

878
01:21:31,020 --> 01:21:33,340
偷袭成功

879
01:21:33,630 --> 01:21:35,430
1943年5月16日

880
01:21:35,430 --> 01:21:37,460
那栋楼...

881
01:21:45,220 --> 01:21:47,300
转过去

882
01:21:54,170 --> 01:21:55,900
开枪

883
01:22:20,400 --> 01:22:21,590
谢谢你
Thank you.

884
01:22:25,470 --> 01:22:28,910
-我本想早点来的  但...  -不不不  谢谢你
- I wanted to come earlier,but... - No,thank you.

885
01:22:32,780 --> 01:22:35,180
没人想到会他们会坚持这么久
No one thought they'd hold out so long.

886
01:22:36,850 --> 01:22:38,080
我不应该出来的
I never should've come out.

887
01:22:38,220 --> 01:22:39,310
我应该留在那里  与他们一起战斗
I should have stayed and fought with them.

888
01:22:39,450 --> 01:22:41,250
瓦列  别那么说
Wladyslaw,stop that.

889
01:22:41,390 --> 01:22:43,010
现在都结束了
It's over now.

890
01:22:43,160 --> 01:22:45,120
你该为他们感到骄傲
Just be proud of them.

891
01:22:46,260 --> 01:22:48,560
天啊  他们发起了抗争
My God,did they put up a fight?

892
01:22:48,630 --> 01:22:50,260
没错
Yes.

893
01:22:51,860 --> 01:22:53,130
德国人发动了战斗
So did the Germans.

894
01:22:53,270 --> 01:22:54,730
他们非常震惊
They were in shock!

895
01:22:54,870 --> 01:22:57,860
他们没有预料到  没有人预料得到
They didn't expect it. Nobody expected it.

896
01:22:58,000 --> 01:23:00,670
犹太人反击了
Jews fighting back.

897
01:23:00,810 --> 01:23:02,570
谁会想到呢
Who would thought?

898
01:23:02,710 --> 01:23:05,370
这样做有什么好处呢
What good did it do?

899
01:23:05,510 --> 01:23:07,670
什么好处
What good?

900
01:23:07,810 --> 01:23:10,480
瓦列 你真让我吃惊
Wladek,I'm surprised with you.

901
01:23:10,620 --> 01:23:13,410
他们尊严地死去  这就是好处
They died with dignity.That what good they did.

902
01:23:14,290 --> 01:23:15,690
你还知道别的吗
And you know something else?

903
01:23:16,320 --> 01:23:17,910
现在波兰人要反抗
Now the Poles will rise.

904
01:23:18,690 --> 01:23:19,890
我们准备好了
We are ready.

905
01:23:20,630 --> 01:23:23,420
我们也要抗争  你知道吗
We'll fight too. You see.

906
01:23:38,640 --> 01:23:41,110
把你的东西收拾好  你必需离开
Get your things together.You have to leave.

907
01:23:41,250 --> 01:23:45,120
怎么  发生什么事了
What? What's happened?

908
01:23:46,250 --> 01:23:47,380
我要逃亡了
I'm on the run.

909
01:23:47,590 --> 01:23:48,380
发生什么事了
What's happened?

910
01:23:48,590 --> 01:23:50,560
秘密警察发现我们的武器了
The Gestapo found our weapons.

911
01:23:51,590 --> 01:23:53,580
他们已经逮捕了嘉琳娜和安德兹
They've arrested Janina and Andrzej.

912
01:23:53,790 --> 01:23:56,110
他们也将要查出这个地方
They're bound to find out about this place too.

913
01:23:56,580 --> 01:23:57,890
你必需马上离开
 You must get away at once.

914
01:23:58,020 --> 01:23:59,100
你要我到哪里去
Where do you want me to go?

915
01:24:00,500 --> 01:24:01,500
看着我
Look at me,

916
01:24:01,860 --> 01:24:03,120
我不要走
I'm not leaving.

917
01:24:04,990 --> 01:24:06,220
我不能留在这里  冒险一试吗
Can I take my chances here?

918
01:24:06,320 --> 01:24:07,280
11你自己决定
That's your decision.

919
01:24:07,630 --> 01:24:11,330
但是当他们突击公寓的时候  从窗户跳出去
But when they storm the flat,throw yourself out the  window...

920
01:24:11,440 --> 01:24:12,670
别让他们活捉你
don't let them get you alive.

921
01:24:13,130 --> 01:24:15,450
我身上有毒药   他们也不可能活捉我
I have poison on me. They won't get me alive either.

922
01:27:31,850 --> 01:27:34,680
开门
Open  up!

923
01:27:38,240 --> 01:27:40,410
马上开门  不然我们要叫警察来了
Open the door or we'll call the police!

924
01:28:10,090 --> 01:28:11,730
你是这栋公寓的人吗
Are you from this flat?

925
01:28:12,370 --> 01:28:13,980
你没有登记
You're not registered.

926
01:28:14,110 --> 01:28:15,450
这是我朋友的房子
It belongs to a friend of mine.

927
01:28:15,690 --> 01:28:17,870
我只是来拜访他   但他不在家
I just came to visit,but not,I just missed him.

928
01:28:17,990 --> 01:28:19,320
你有身份证吗
Have you got your identity card?

929
01:28:20,550 --> 01:28:22,620
让我看你的身份证
Let me see your identity card.

930
01:28:22,720 --> 01:28:23,360
好的
Yes,of course.

931
01:28:26,560 --> 01:28:27,880
我要看你的身份证
I want to see your identity card!

932
01:28:28,130 --> 01:28:28,880
怎么了
What's happening?

933
01:28:29,010 --> 01:28:33,500
他是犹太人  犹太人  拦住这个犹太人
He's a Jew! A Jew! Stop the Jew!

934
01:28:35,350 --> 01:28:38,420
别让他出去  拦住他
Don't let him out!Stop him!

935
01:29:51,230 --> 01:29:51,680
谁
Yes?

936
01:29:52,800 --> 01:29:54,220
11吉勃克辛斯基先生要我来的
Mr. Gebczynski sent me.

937
01:30:01,700 --> 01:30:03,440
瓦列迪斯洛·席皮尔曼
Wladyslaw Szpilman.

938
01:30:04,480 --> 01:30:04,920
多萝塔
Dorota.

939
01:30:06,690 --> 01:30:08,020
进来
Come in.

940
01:30:15,640 --> 01:30:16,940
抱歉  我...
I'm sorry.I...

941
01:30:17,480 --> 01:30:19,150
抱歉  有人给我这个地址
I'm sorry.I was given this address.

942
01:30:19,290 --> 01:30:21,230
我来找一位德兹奇威兹先生
and I'm looking for a Mr. Dzikiewicz.

943
01:30:21,570 --> 01:30:24,290
麦克·德兹奇威兹是我的丈夫
Michael Dzikiewicz,he's my husband.

944
01:30:24,870 --> 01:30:26,020
进来
Come in.

945
01:30:34,860 --> 01:30:36,120
坐
Sit.

946
01:30:40,140 --> 01:30:41,400
我需要帮助
I need help.

947
01:30:43,050 --> 01:30:46,010
他会在宵禁之前回来
He'll be back before curfew.

948
01:30:46,010 --> 01:30:48,700
我一直在躲藏
I've been in hiding.

949
01:30:50,610 --> 01:30:52,240
我需要一个藏身之处
I need somewhere to stay.

950
01:30:53,080 --> 01:30:54,340
他就快回来了
Be here soon.

951
01:30:56,920 --> 01:30:58,580
你结婚多久了
How long have you been married?

952
01:30:58,950 --> 01:31:00,320
才满一年
Just over a year.

953
01:31:03,090 --> 01:31:05,110
裘瑞克怎么样了
And how is Jurek?

954
01:31:05,760 --> 01:31:06,850
死了
Dead.

955
01:31:14,200 --> 01:31:16,190
你的宝宝什么时候出世
When is your baby due?

956
01:31:16,340 --> 01:31:18,460
圣诞节
Christmas.

957
01:31:18,640 --> 01:31:21,610
现在不是养育小孩的好时机  但当时...
This is not a good time to have children,but then...

958
01:31:24,840 --> 01:31:27,970
这是我先生  这是瓦列迪斯洛·席皮尔曼
This is my husband. Wladyslaw Szpilman.

959
01:31:28,510 --> 01:31:30,910
马里克·吉勃克辛斯基要他来的
Marek Gebczynski sent him.

960
01:31:31,050 --> 01:31:32,310
是的  我记得
Yes,I remember.

961
01:31:35,120 --> 01:31:37,750
吉勃克辛斯基说过只有在紧急时才来找你
Mr. Gebczynski said to contact you only in case of emergency.

962
01:31:37,890 --> 01:31:39,150
现在不用担心了
Don't worry now.

963
01:31:48,800 --> 01:31:52,130
今晚我们不能把你送走  你就睡在沙发
We can't move you tonight.You'll sleep on the sofa.

964
01:31:56,840 --> 01:31:59,400
不好意思
Excuse me.

965
01:32:03,420 --> 01:32:05,780
抱歉  我可以吃片面包吗
I'm sorry,could I have a piece of bread?

966
01:32:06,620 --> 01:32:08,480
当然  我们一起吃
Yes,of course.We will eat.

967
01:32:10,120 --> 01:32:12,390
坐  请坐
Sit. Please,sit.

968
01:32:13,960 --> 01:32:15,020
谢谢你
Thank you.

969
01:34:24,020 --> 01:34:25,610
你现在正置身德国区
You're on a very German area.

970
01:34:27,290 --> 01:34:28,130
对面的建筑物是一家医院
Building on the opposite is a hospital

971
01:34:28,290 --> 01:34:29,920
收容从俄国前线回来的伤兵
taking wounded from the Russian front.

972
01:34:33,530 --> 01:34:35,260
它隔壁就是纳粹党卫军
And next door is the Schutzpolizei.

973
01:34:38,300 --> 01:34:39,630
最安全的地方
Safest place to be.

974
01:34:40,710 --> 01:34:42,570
就是在狮子巢穴的正中心
Right at the heart of the lion's den.

975
01:34:48,850 --> 01:34:50,110
我要把你锁在里面
I'll be locking you in.

976
01:34:51,250 --> 01:34:54,580
没有人知道你在这里  所以尽可能保持安静
No one knows you're here,so keep as quiet as possible.

977
01:37:04,620 --> 01:37:05,810
还好吧
All well?

978
01:37:07,390 --> 01:37:08,580
谢谢你
Thank you.

979
01:37:13,890 --> 01:37:15,550
这位是安提克·札勒斯
This is Antek Szalas.

980
01:37:15,930 --> 01:37:17,090
他将会照顾你
He'll be looking after you.

981
01:37:17,930 --> 01:37:19,830
-你好  -你好
- How do you do? - How do you do?

982
01:37:19,970 --> 01:37:20,950
谢谢你
Thank you.

983
01:37:21,900 --> 01:37:24,200
我已经给了他一把备用钥匙
I've given him a second key.

984
01:37:24,340 --> 01:37:26,400
他会带食物给你  看你是否安然无恙
He'll bring food,see that you're alright.

985
01:37:27,440 --> 01:37:29,240
他是地下组织成员  人很好
He's with the underground,he's a good man.

986
01:37:34,110 --> 01:37:36,050
你不记得我了  席皮尔曼先生
You don't remember me?Mr Szpilman.

987
01:37:37,050 --> 01:37:38,140
我想不记得了
I don't think so.

988
01:37:38,720 --> 01:37:41,810
华沙广播电台  我是一个技术人员
Warsaw Radio. I was a technician.

989
01:37:42,550 --> 01:37:44,150
我几乎每天都看见你
I saw you almost everyday.

990
01:37:46,290 --> 01:37:47,880
抱歉  我不记得了  我...
I'm sorry,I don't remember.I...

991
01:37:48,030 --> 01:37:49,290
没有关系
It doesn't matter.

992
01:37:52,000 --> 01:37:54,730
你不用担心任何事情  我会常来看你的
You've nothing to worry about. I'll visit often.

993
01:37:56,670 --> 01:37:58,800
你会很高兴听到联军正在轰炸德国...
You'll be pleased to hear that the Allies are bombing Germany...

994
01:37:59,240 --> 01:38:01,100
夜复一夜  夜复一夜
night after night,after night.

995
01:38:01,770 --> 01:38:04,000
科隆  汉堡  柏林
Cologne,Hamburg,Berlin.

996
01:38:04,140 --> 01:38:06,300
而俄国人将会真正把他们带入地狱
And the Russians are really giving them hell.

997
01:38:06,450 --> 01:38:07,670
这是终结的开始
It's the beginning of the end.

998
01:38:07,810 --> 01:38:09,040
但愿如此
Oh,Let's hope so.

999
01:38:20,210 --> 01:38:22,420
过来

1000
01:38:22,590 --> 01:38:24,800
小心点

1001
01:38:25,720 --> 01:38:28,680
就是那个  小心点

1002
01:38:55,490 --> 01:38:56,960
还活着吗
Still alive then?

1003
01:39:01,670 --> 01:39:05,070
这里有香肠  面包
Here. Sausage,bread.

1004
01:39:05,970 --> 01:39:07,630
那瓶伏特加还没喝完吗
You still got that vodka?

1005
01:39:22,290 --> 01:39:24,620
这还得持续多久呢
How long is this meant to last?

1006
01:39:24,760 --> 01:39:25,850
不久了
Not long now.

1007
01:39:27,190 --> 01:39:29,420
我...我想...我得了黄疸
I thin…think I've got jaundice.

1008
01:39:30,530 --> 01:39:31,790
别担心那个
You don't worry about that.

1009
01:39:33,400 --> 01:39:34,860
它只是让你看起来比较好笑
Just makes you look funny.

1010
01:39:35,570 --> 01:39:38,900
我爷爷当年出黄疸时被他女朋友甩了
My grandfather was jilted by his girlfriend when he got jaundice.

1011
01:39:39,770 --> 01:39:40,860
喝光它
Drink up.

1012
01:39:42,540 --> 01:39:44,060
为...为什么你不早一点来
Why...why didn't you come sooner?

1013
01:39:44,210 --> 01:39:45,540
已经超过二个礼拜了
It's been over two weeks...

1014
01:39:45,680 --> 01:39:47,580
出什么问题了吗
Problems.

1015
01:39:47,710 --> 01:39:49,340
钱
Money.

1016
01:39:50,250 --> 01:39:51,940
我必需筹钱买食物
I've got to raise money to buy the food.

1017
01:39:53,150 --> 01:39:54,640
我需要可以卖的东西
I need things to sell,

1018
01:39:54,790 --> 01:39:56,050
这不容易
it's not easy.

1019
01:40:00,660 --> 01:40:02,890
这个  把它卖了
Here. Sell this.

1020
01:40:05,860 --> 01:40:07,660
食物比时间重要
Food is more important than time.

1021
01:40:12,540 --> 01:40:14,770
对了  我要告诉你
Oh,yes. I meant to tell you!

1022
01:40:14,910 --> 01:40:16,500
联军已经在法国登陆了
The Allies have landed in France.

1023
01:40:16,640 --> 01:40:18,270
俄国军队就快要到这里了
Russians will be here soon.

1024
01:40:19,380 --> 01:40:21,210
他们会把狗娘养的德国人赶走...
They'll beat the shit out of the Germans...

1025
01:40:23,180 --> 01:40:24,510
随时都可能到
any day now.

1026
01:41:04,290 --> 01:41:06,050
不  不  不
No No No

1027
01:41:09,190 --> 01:41:10,290
瓦列
Wladek?

1028
01:41:15,770 --> 01:41:16,990
瓦列
Wladek?

1029
01:41:19,870 --> 01:41:23,400
我就知道  我就知道这会发生
I knew it.I knew this would happen.

1030
01:41:25,810 --> 01:41:27,970
-我要去找医生  -你不能去  这样太危险了
- I'll get a doctor - You can't. It's too dangerous.

1031
01:41:28,110 --> 01:41:29,810
我去找路札克医生  我们可以信任他
Dr. Luczak. We can trust him.

1032
01:41:29,950 --> 01:41:32,040
多萝塔  别傻了  他是儿科医生
Ridiculous.Don't be stupid.He's a pediatrician.

1033
01:41:32,180 --> 01:41:33,210
他也是医生
He's still a doctor.

1034
01:41:33,350 --> 01:41:37,580
不  你留下  我去找
No.You stay. I'll go.

1035
01:42:11,190 --> 01:42:12,680
我们是来道别的
We came to say goodbye.

1036
01:42:14,290 --> 01:42:17,230
我们要到奥特沃茨克跟我妈妈在一起
We're going to stay with my mother in Otwocks.

1037
01:42:17,430 --> 01:42:20,300
宝宝已经在那里了  那里更安全
The baby is already there.It's safer.

1038
01:42:20,930 --> 01:42:23,660
据说暴动随时都有可能开始
There's talk that the uprising will begin any day now.

1039
01:42:26,340 --> 01:42:28,530
札勒斯可能被射杀了
That man Szalas should be shot.

1040
01:42:29,970 --> 01:42:34,240
他为了你在华沙到处募款
He's been collecting money on your behalf all over Warsaw.

1041
01:42:34,980 --> 01:42:37,310
显然人们慷慨解囊
Apparently people gave generously,

1042
01:42:37,950 --> 01:42:39,940
所以他筹到了一笔可观的数目
so he collected a tidy sum.

1043
01:42:44,150 --> 01:42:45,920
天啊
My God.

1044
01:42:50,260 --> 01:42:52,090
肝脏肿得像颗橄榄球
The liver the size of a football.

1045
01:42:52,230 --> 01:42:54,160
胆囊有严重的发炎
Inflammation of the gall bladder...

1046
01:42:56,200 --> 01:42:57,130
但他会活着
but he'll live.

1047
01:43:00,770 --> 01:43:02,970
我会试着给他找些果糖
I'll try to get him some laevulose,

1048
01:43:03,110 --> 01:43:04,270
但这并不容易
but it's not easy.

1049
01:43:05,310 --> 01:43:07,000
你可以再来看他吗
Can you visit him again?

1050
01:43:07,710 --> 01:43:08,770
我也不确定
Who knows.

1051
01:43:08,910 --> 01:43:09,740
医生
Doctor?

1052
01:43:11,080 --> 01:43:13,740
-谢谢你  -别说话  休息
- thank you. - Don't speak,rest.

1053
01:43:16,890 --> 01:43:18,220
非常感激你过来
Thank you so much for coming.

1054
01:43:21,130 --> 01:43:22,650
我们给你带来一些食物
We brought you some food.

1055
01:43:23,560 --> 01:43:25,220
现在我要为你准备些东西
I'll prepare something now for you,

1056
01:43:25,430 --> 01:43:27,190
然后我们就得走了
then we must go.

1057
01:43:32,900 --> 01:43:35,570
1944年8月1日

1058
01:44:19,360 --> 01:44:21,910
那里有个受伤的人

1059
01:44:22,410 --> 01:44:24,950
出来

1060
01:44:25,080 --> 01:44:27,500
当心点  当心点

1061
01:44:28,620 --> 01:44:31,580
-我去找人帮忙  -快点

1062
01:44:32,250 --> 01:44:36,260
赶紧  把担架抬过来

1063
01:44:40,090 --> 01:44:42,720
退到里边去

1064
01:46:29,850 --> 01:46:31,640
出去
get out

1065
01:46:31,780 --> 01:46:33,770
出去  出去  快到街上去
get out!get out!get out the street!

1066
01:46:33,920 --> 01:46:34,910
到街上去
get out the street!

1067
01:46:35,050 --> 01:46:37,540
现在出去  德国人已经把这栋楼给包围了
Get out now! The Germans have surrounded the building!

1068
01:47:19,800 --> 01:47:23,760
来人啊  来人啊  快来人帮我
Somebody...Somebody help me!

1069
01:48:21,730 --> 01:48:24,900
你还好吗  这里太脏了

1070
01:48:25,280 --> 01:48:29,860
我来检查这边  不用担心

1071
01:48:30,070 --> 01:48:32,530
仔细点

1072
01:48:37,960 --> 01:48:40,630
-亨里齐  -我正在检查

1073
01:48:43,170 --> 01:48:45,710
有人吗

1074
01:48:49,800 --> 01:48:53,930
-快下来  -好的  这就下来

1075
01:53:02,140 --> 01:53:03,970
快点  把他们都堆在一起

1076
01:53:10,310 --> 01:53:12,520
扔过去

1077
01:54:36,770 --> 01:54:39,730
要把所有的东西都做上标记

1078
01:54:40,780 --> 01:54:41,740
快点

1079
02:01:43,030 --> 02:01:44,690
你在这里做什么

1080
02:01:49,630 --> 02:01:51,120
你是谁

1081
02:01:56,070 --> 02:01:57,370
听的懂吗

1082
02:01:58,740 --> 02:01:59,710
是

1083
02:02:02,110 --> 02:02:03,480
你在做什么

1084
02:02:09,150 --> 02:02:10,810
我...

1085
02:02:12,120 --> 02:02:14,520
我试着要把罐头打开

1086
02:02:15,960 --> 02:02:17,390
你住在这里吗

1087
02:02:21,100 --> 02:02:23,120
你在这里工作吗

1088
02:02:23,270 --> 02:02:25,170
不

1089
02:02:28,670 --> 02:02:29,970
你的职业是什么

1090
02:02:33,540 --> 02:02:35,170
我...

1091
02:02:37,550 --> 02:02:39,670
我是钢琴师

1092
02:02:42,590 --> 02:02:43,950
钢琴师

1093
02:03:03,670 --> 02:03:04,660
来啊

1094
02:03:30,600 --> 02:03:31,790
弹吧

1095
02:08:51,990 --> 02:08:53,920
你躲在这里吗

1096
02:08:59,630 --> 02:09:00,960
犹太人?

1097
02:09:04,070 --> 02:09:05,730
你躲在哪里

1098
02:09:08,370 --> 02:09:09,500
阁楼

1099
02:09:13,640 --> 02:09:14,700
带我去看

1100
02:09:39,300 --> 02:09:40,560
你有吃的吗

1101
02:10:27,930 --> 02:10:33,520
他们说  这非常的重要...

1102
02:10:40,400 --> 02:10:41,490
立正

1103
02:10:43,830 --> 02:10:44,660
早安

1104
02:10:44,800 --> 02:10:46,360
早安上校

1105
02:11:52,200 --> 02:11:53,400
犹太人

1106
02:12:08,550 --> 02:12:10,380
对不起  请问...

1107
02:12:10,450 --> 02:12:12,890
那些炮火是怎么回事

1108
02:12:13,020 --> 02:12:15,460
俄国人正要渡河

1109
02:12:17,090 --> 02:12:20,220
你只需再等两个礼拜就够了

1110
02:13:51,650 --> 02:13:52,880
发生什么事了

1111
02:13:53,020 --> 02:13:54,580
我们要撤退了

1112
02:13:57,730 --> 02:13:59,420
俄国人来了吗

1113
02:13:59,560 --> 02:14:00,550
还没

1114
02:14:04,030 --> 02:14:09,230
我不知道该怎么感谢你

1115
02:14:09,410 --> 02:14:11,900
感谢上帝  不用谢我

1116
02:14:12,040 --> 02:14:14,030
他让我们死里逃生

1117
02:14:14,180 --> 02:14:17,370
这就是为什么我们要信仰他

1118
02:14:29,220 --> 02:14:30,190
给你  拿着

1119
02:14:31,930 --> 02:14:32,920
你呢

1120
02:14:33,060 --> 02:14:34,120
我还有一件

1121
02:14:34,260 --> 02:14:35,590
那件更暖和

1122
02:14:40,600 --> 02:14:43,130
战争结束后你要做什么

1123
02:14:45,970 --> 02:14:48,500
我会继续在波兰电台

1124
02:14:49,240 --> 02:14:50,710
弹钢琴

1125
02:14:51,280 --> 02:14:52,980
告诉我你的名字

1126
02:14:53,120 --> 02:14:54,810
也许我会来听你演奏

1127
02:14:56,050 --> 02:14:57,350
席皮尔曼

1128
02:14:58,490 --> 02:14:59,890
席皮尔曼

1129
02:15:02,460 --> 02:15:04,890
对钢琴师来说这是个好名字

1130
02:16:27,710 --> 02:16:30,200
德国人  德国人
German! German!

1131
02:16:51,430 --> 02:16:56,200
不  不要开枪  我是波兰人
Don't shoot, I'm Polish!

1132
02:16:56,970 --> 02:16:58,460
我是波兰人
I'm Polish!

1133
02:16:59,510 --> 02:17:01,170
出来  举起双手
Come out with your hands up!

1134
02:17:01,380 --> 02:17:02,780
拜托  我求求你
Please! I beg of you!

1135
02:17:03,380 --> 02:17:06,710
不要开枪  不要开枪  我求求你
Don't shoot, don't shoot.I beg you,

1136
02:17:06,850 --> 02:17:08,010
我是波兰人
I'm a Polish.

1137
02:17:08,150 --> 02:17:09,740
下来
Come down!

1138
02:17:13,990 --> 02:17:17,050
拜托  我是波兰人  拜托
Please, I'm Polish.Please

1139
02:17:17,190 --> 02:17:20,220
拜托  他是波兰人
Please.He's Polish.

1140
02:17:23,270 --> 02:17:25,100
是的  他是波兰人
Yes, he's Polish.

1141
02:17:26,700 --> 02:17:28,430
这件该死的外套是怎么回事
Why the fucking coat?

1142
02:17:30,310 --> 02:17:31,530
我很冷
I'm cold.

1143
02:17:51,560 --> 02:17:54,190
看看他们  婊子养的德国人
Look at them.German fuckers!

1144
02:17:55,060 --> 02:17:57,730
凶手  凶手
Murderers! Murderers!

1145
02:17:58,270 --> 02:18:00,330
肮脏的狗杂种
Dirty bastards!

1146
02:18:00,840 --> 02:18:02,860
杀人魔  杂种
Assassins! Bastards!

1147
02:18:03,440 --> 02:18:07,680
看看你们现在  你们夺走了我的一切
Look at you now! You took everything I had.

1148
02:18:07,680 --> 02:18:10,650
我是个音乐家  你们夺走了我的小提琴
Me, a musician.You took my violin,

1149
02:18:10,780 --> 02:18:13,250
狗娘养的  你们夺走我的灵魂
you took my soul.

1150
02:18:17,690 --> 02:18:19,360
音乐家
Musician?

1151
02:18:20,790 --> 02:18:22,350
你是音乐家
Are you a musician?

1152
02:18:22,890 --> 02:18:23,520
是
yeah

1153
02:18:23,660 --> 02:18:25,890
那么  你认识
Do you know...

1154
02:18:26,030 --> 02:18:28,190
钢琴家席皮尔曼吗
a pianist called Szpilman,

1155
02:18:28,400 --> 02:18:29,490
他是为波兰电台演奏的
from the Polish radio station?

1156
02:18:29,630 --> 02:18:31,720
我当然认识他
Of course I know him.

1157
02:18:31,870 --> 02:18:35,360
他在避难时  我帮助过他
I helped him to hide himself.

1158
02:18:35,470 --> 02:18:37,900
告诉他我在这里
Tell him I'm here.

1159
02:18:38,040 --> 02:18:39,800
请他帮助我
Ask him to help me.

1160
02:18:43,610 --> 02:18:44,980
-你叫什么名字  -霍森菲尔
- What's your name? - Hosenfeld.

1161
02:18:46,550 --> 02:18:48,410
什么
What?

1162
02:20:30,020 --> 02:20:31,920
就是这里  我很确定
It was here, I'm certain of it.

1163
02:20:34,620 --> 02:20:36,090
但现在已经不在了
Well, it's not here now.

1164
02:20:36,990 --> 02:20:38,480
我对着他们咆哮
I shouted, abused them.

1165
02:20:38,630 --> 02:20:41,190
我现在一点也不觉得骄傲  但我当时就是那样做的
I'm not proud of it, but that's what I did.

1166
02:20:41,400 --> 02:20:43,590
我当年就站在你现在这个位置
I stood where you are now.

1167
02:20:43,730 --> 02:20:44,990
那儿围着有刺的铁丝网
There was a barbed wire

1168
02:20:45,130 --> 02:20:46,900
那个德国军官向我走来
and this German came up to me.

1169
02:20:48,640 --> 02:20:50,260
你没听到他的名字吗
You didn't catch his name?

1170
02:20:50,410 --> 02:20:51,370
没有
No.

1171
02:20:54,480 --> 02:20:56,640
我去那间工厂问问  也许他们知道些什么
I'll ask at the factory.They may know something.

1172
02:22:01,810 --> 02:22:05,940
瓦列迪斯洛·席皮尔曼  继续住在华沙  直到去世

1173
02:22:06,080 --> 02:22:08,170
他逝于2000年7月6日  享年88岁

1174
02:22:17,560 --> 02:22:20,790
那个德国军官的名字是威廉·霍森菲尔

1175
02:22:21,630 --> 02:22:25,160
仅知他于1952年死在俄国的战俘营

1176
02:22:30,440 --> 02:22:32,840
剧终

